【music】
【音樂】
Academia Sinica's Knowledge Experience in August Kebo Lectures and Speeches Begin
中央研究院知識想驗8月份科博講座演講會開始
We invite Vice President Huang Jingxin to host for us
我們請黃靜新副院長為我們主持
【applause】
【拍手】
First of all, on behalf of Academia Sinica, welcome all distinguished guests
這個首先代表中央研究院歡迎各位貴賓
Well, today is Professor Ying Qingsun's lecture
那今天是這個影慶孫教授的講演
So this is also a speech he gave before he retired.
那這也是他退休前的一個講演
But don't worry, he didn't just retire
但是大家不要緊張他不是剛才退休
He will retire in 2021
他2021才退休的啊
so i just
所以我剛才
I was also very nervous just now, such an important scholar is going to retire soon
剛才也很緊張 這麼重要的學者馬上就要退休了
I'm not ready yet
我心裡都還沒準備
I am in charge of major research in the humanities and social sciences
我是負責重要研究人文跟社會科學
So I'm right about this
所以我對這個
Special care for the dynamics of our outstanding academics
我們優秀的學者的動態特別的關心
then let me introduce
那我現在就介紹一下
Shadow Youth Professor
影青春教授
Maybe some people think of him as a very herdsman
也許有些人對他這個非常的牧民
know him well
已經對他很了解
But I still have to be reasonable
不過我還是要行理如以
say a few words
講幾句話
Professor Naying Youth
那影青春教授
he is american
他是美國
Ph.D., Department of Sociology, Minsota Zhouli University
Minsota 周力大學的社會學系的博士
Now it is the Institute of Sociology of our school
現在是本院社會學研究所
Distinguished Researcher
特聘研究員
The specially-appointed researcher is from the university.
那特聘研究員就是大學裡面的
lecture professor meaning
講座教授的意思
What about research interests?
那研究興趣呢
major in family sociology
主要為家庭社會學
youth development
青少年發展
women role
婦女角色
Chen Dannai International
陳丹奈國際
Member of the Executive Committee of the Sociological Society ISA
社會學社 ISA 執行委員會的委員
Chair of the Family Research Committee
家庭研究委員會的主席
Currently serving as the editor of several domestic and foreign academic journals
目前一擔任數個國內外學術期刊的
Editorial Board and Advisors
編輯委員和顧問
Host and participate in various academic projects
主持和參與多項學術計畫
Including the period from 1991 to 1994
包括 1991 年到 1994 年的
Survey on Social Image in Taiwan
台灣社會意象調查
2004 to 2007
2004 年至 2007 年
Refers to the intergenerational inheritance of virtual values
指擬價值觀的代間傳承
and from 1997 to 2020
以及 1997 年至 2020 年的
The growth history of Taiwanese teenagers, etc.
台灣青少年成長的歷程等
his scholarly works
他的學術著作專書
Focus on family studies and youth studies
以家庭研究和青少年研究為主
Psychological Welfare Included
包括的 Psychological Welfare
Israel Youth 2013
Israel Youth 2013 年
forthcoming
即將出版之
Qian Jun Taiwan
千軍 台灣
Academic Issues of Feminist
Feminist的學術專刊
What about today, Professor Ying Qingchun?
今天呢 穎清春教授呢
will explain to us that there is a hospital
將為我們解說有本院
A long-term research project driven by society
社會所所推動的一項長期研究計畫
is from 2000
是從2000年起
Continue to track the progress of Guoyi and Guoshan
持續追蹤當年國藝和國山的
teen growth trajectory
青少年 成長軌跡
so we have someone here
所以我們在座就有人是這個
Those in the investigation have become adults
調查裡面的已經變成大人的
the young man's child
這個年輕人的小孩子
This long-term follow-up
這項長期的追蹤
The Growth Process of Taiwanese Teenagers
台灣青少年的成長歷程
and social context research
和社會脈絡的研究
Attempt to explore family education from it
試圖從中探討家庭 教育
interaction with society
和社會三方面的交互影響
and the difficulty of constructing localized research
並建構本土化的研究難途
It is hoped that the results of the study
希望在研究結果
Proposed to influence the youth of the society
提出影響社會青少年
Important Factors in the Growth Process
成長歷程的重要因素
His speech must be wonderful
他的演講一定精彩可期
Let's applaud Dr. Ying
讓我們鼓掌歡迎影博士
Thanks
謝謝
you are the one, aren't you?
您是那個是吧
you have to stand
你要站在座的
It doesn't matter if you can sit here
座的話可以坐這裡沒關係
Standing like this
站在座好像是這個
open it first
要先打開一下
Thank you Vice President Huang
謝謝黃副院長
It's really an honor to have the opportunity to represent the research group
真的是非常榮幸能夠有機會代表研究小組
Come share our research results with you
來跟大家分享我們的研究成果
Last time at this place was June 2010
上一次在這個地方是2010年的6月
At that time, the first phase of our follow-up study
那個時候我們追蹤研究的第一個階段
just came to an end
剛剛告一個段落
so i'm joking
所以我在開玩笑說
Our humanities and social sciences seem to have to be taught every 10 years
我們人文社會科學好像要每10年講一遍
So I probably won't have time to report the update to you next year
所以我大概明年來不及跟大家報告更新的東西
So when I was preparing this speech myself,
所以我自己在預備這份演講的時候
I am very grateful
心裡是很感恩的
then later
那麼待會就
Because I really want to share such rich results with you.
因為實在很想跟大家分享這麼豐富的成果
hang again
又一直掛一露彎
So I keep changing the powerpoint to 6:10
所以我一直把powerpoint改到6點10分
so now what
所以現在呢
I try my best to speak
我盡我的力講
Please cheer up everyone
那麻煩各位這個提起精神
I speak faster and faster
我講話會越講越快
that's
那可是
I will try my best to make everyone understand
我會盡量講的大家都聽得懂
especially i'm glad to know
尤其我很高興知道
Some of the respondents to our straight talk in-depth interviews
我們直話深入訪談的一些受訪者
here today
今天也在這個地方
i don't know where you are
我不知道你們在哪裡
but hope you know
不過希望你們知道
Your academic contribution is very great
你們對學術貢獻是非常大的
Thanks
謝謝
good
好
give me this
這個給我
where do i press
我按哪裡啊
good
好
Simply put, before starting
簡單來講在開始之前
I want to represent
我要代表
Our research group is mainly composed of sociologists and social psychologists
我們研究小組當中主要是社會學者和社會心理學者所合作的
So
那麼
what our research cares
我們的研究關懷是什麼
I said that we are often more concerned about structural factors
我說我們常常比較關懷的是結構的因素
Personal factors are also important
個人的因素也很重要
But we may be more concerned with structural factors
可是我們可能更關心結構的因素
People like to see some short-term effects
大家很喜歡看一些短期效果
We pay more attention to some long-term effects
我們比較重視的是一些長期的效應
in addition
另外
cultural norms
到底是文化規範
Great influence on people
對人的影響大
Or personal education income, etc.
還是個人教育收入等等
How high is this personal resource?
這個個人資源高呢
Then these influences
那麼這些影響之外
There are also some data for our reference
還有一些數據資料都是我們參考
I simply use an example to illustrate
我簡單用一個例子來做說明
I think maybe everyone will understand
我想也許大家就會理解
We all know that divorce research is very important
大家都知道離婚研究非常重要
Probably the world has
大概這個世界上已經
More than thousands of academic research reports
不只數千篇上萬篇的學術研究報告
Most divorce studies are
大多數的離婚研究是
Focus on the reasons for divorce between husband and wife
著重在個人夫跟妻之間為什麼離婚
Then tell you that the relationship is not good
然後就跟你說關係不好
Because they have different money levels, etc.
因為他們金錢關不同等等等等
this is very important
這個都很重要
However, sociological research is more concerned with structural factors
可是社會學的研究比較在乎結構因素
That is to say, when the husband and wife are two people
就是說當這個夫跟妻兩個人
As soon as it is shown, the difference in education level is greater
一擺出來教育程度差越大
The greater the difference in financial background between the two growth backgrounds
兩方面成長背景的財力背景差越大
or his whole body
或者他整個人
The greater the difference in life experience, the greater the difference in these structural experiences
人生經驗差越大,這些結構經驗差越大的時候
The probability of his divorce has increased significantly
他離婚可能性就顯著的提高
So let's say it again, what we're going to say later
那麼我們再一遍講,我們等一下要講的
All findings do not refer to a single person
所有的發現都不是指某一個人
Rather, it is a pattern that is pronounced across the majority
而是整個大多數人當中顯著的模式
So there are always some surprises
所以常常有一些意外呢
These journalism scholars are very interested
這些新聞學者就很有興趣
To report these special circumstances
要報告這些特殊的情況
We want to know too, but we want to know more
我們也很想知道,不過我們更想知道
what most people look like
大多數人是長什麼樣子
But I just said that we are right about the structural factors
不過我剛講我們對的結構因素
Because Huang Fu is here
因為黃富在這個地方
There's nothing we can do when we meet historians
我們遇到歷史學家就沒有辦法
Because, our...
因為呢,我們的...
like that divorce study tells us
像那個離婚的研究告訴我們
when the country is at war
當這個國家發生戰爭的時候
That divorce rate is soaring
那個離婚率是飆升的
Fortunately , wars don't happen every day
好在的,戰爭不是每天發生
That is the structural factor at least exists
那可是結構因素至少是存在的
probably like this
大概這樣
In today's report, I will probably focus on the first two aspects.
那今天報告大概其實我會著重在前面兩個方面
Because it's a...
因為這是一個...
Long-term research, especially with many colleagues among us and our sample
長期的研究,尤其我們當中又有許多的同仁以及我們的樣本
I will explain the whole research plan to you.
我把整個研究規劃跟大家做個說明
Then I try to succinctly divide the findings of our research into three parts
然後我盡量的精簡地把我們研究的發現分成三個部分來說
In terms of family, in terms of education, in terms of marriage and childbearing in this generation
從家庭方面,從教育方面,從這個世代的婚姻與生育方面
I am very grateful that this project over the years is mainly from the Academia Sinica Theme Research Project
我非常感謝過去這麼多年來這個計畫主要是從中研院主題研究計畫
There is also support from the Ministry of Science and Technology, the former National Science Council, and social institutes.
還有科技部,以前的國科會的支持以及社會所
Fine fee support can only continue until now
精費支持才能持續到現在
Our research team, this is the second phase
我們的研究團隊,這是第二階段的
In the first stage, there are some professors such as Fuyang Zhi who have participated in the
第一階段還有一些像復陽指教授等等曾經參加過
I made this Star sign because I was a postdoctoral fellow in this project
我打這個Star sign,就是曾經在這計畫中當過博士後的
For example, Fan Ganghua, associate professor of Soochow University, is on it
例如在座東吳大學副教授范剛華就在上面
And these are now assistant professors
還有這些就是現在是助理教授
There are different ranks and different schools
有不同的rank跟不同的學校來
Simply put, TYP
簡單來講TYP
I call simplicity TYP, it studies the master
我把簡單叫TYP它研究主子
can be divided into three
可以分成三個
one is that we want to know
一個是我們想要知道
The growth trajectory of contemporary young people
當代年輕人的成長軌跡
We are definitely not the first research team in Taiwan
我們絕對不是台灣第一個研究團隊
do this topic
做這個題目的
New Women Scholars
例如新女學者
they put a lot of emphasis on some development
他們很重視一些發展
They may go from elementary school to junior high school
他們可能從小學做到國中
Or from middle school to high school
或者從初中做到高中
i know on the biological side
我知道在生物那邊
There are also many people doing his fertility development
也有很多人做他生育的發展
But we are from the perspective of social science
可是我們是以社會科學的角度
Especially sociology and family studies orientation
尤其是社會學跟家庭研究的取向
go see this thing
去看這個東西
The second schedule of our positioning
第二個我們的定位的時程
from a life course perspective
是用一個生命歷程取向來看
from early teens
從青少年初期
traced all the way to his young adulthood
一直追蹤到他年輕成人的階段
So it goes through several important life stages
所以會跨好幾個重要的生命階段
The third
第三個
Of course we want to see
我們當然是想要看
Indigenous development model
本土化的發展模式
The vast majority of members were educated in the United States
成員當中絕大多數都是在美國受教育
So for the study of American adolescents
所以對美國青少年研究來講
Their biggest priority is probably nothing more than drug use.
他們最重視的大概就不外乎吸毒
with sex
跟性關係
But then we kept thinking
可是那時候我們一直在想
our middle school kids
我們的國中小孩子
Is this his main life focus
這是他主要的生活的重點嗎
It does not seem
好像不是
So in the last study
所以在上一次研究中
I will specifically report to you
我就特地跟大家報告
Stress cram school results for students and more
生學的壓力補習班的結果等等
Actually that's what they really are
其實那才是他們真的是
second way of life
第二個生活方式
Then we also hope that in the end we can
那我們也希望最後可以在
Influence of social and cultural norms seen in multiple growth trajectories
多元成長軌跡中看到社會與文化規範的影響
So this is what I will say quickly about these three one by one.
那這就是針對這三個我一個一個很快的說
The growth trajectory of young people
年輕人的這個成長軌跡
Have social context, cultural norms, and life experience
有社會脈絡有文化規範有生活經驗
We have been fortunate to have
我們很有幸在過去20年來的時候
just in the whole from
剛好身處於整個從
From collectivism to individualism
集體主義走向個人主義的這個時候
Intergenerational values ​​and attitudes
兩代之間價值觀態度
We hear it all over the place
這各個地方我們都聽到
So we just use a scientific evidence to see
所以我們就是用一個科學的證據去看
what is he
他到底是怎麼一個
In this stage, from 13 years old to 32 years old, there are school diversion and job stratification
這個階段當中,從13歲以上一直到32歲,這裡面有學校的分流,有工作的分層
Then does the young man want to live with his parents, and does he continue to live with his parents after he gets married?
然後年輕人是不是要跟父母同住,他結婚以後是不是還繼續同住
Then when will he leave home? Are there any regional differences? Are there resource considerations?
然後他什麼時候離家,這裡面有沒有一些地區性的差異,有沒有資源上的考量
More importantly, we noticed that when we started, we said we were going to design a scale called parental control of children.
更重要的,我們就注意到當我們開始的時候,我們說我們要設計一個量表叫父母對孩子的管
At that time, the professor of the University of California proposed the concept and there was no scale, so how do you talk about management?
這個管那個時候,加州大學教授提出概念還沒有量表,你要怎麼樣講管
As a result, I didn’t expect our channel to follow all the way. The interviewees among us will know that we often ask you to change it occasionally.
結果沒想到我們這個管一路追蹤我們當中受訪者就會知道,我們常常問你們偶爾會改一下
I found out that Chinese parents, especially Taiwanese parents, still manage their children until they are in their 30s.
就發現這個華人父母,尤其台灣父母對子女的管一直到30多歲還在管
He may say that I don't care about it, I only have one thought that I care about, but more than half of them still continue to care about it.
他也許說我沒有管,我只有一支很關心的念,可是一半以上都還是在繼續的管
In this case, you tell him that children like to be self-reliant
在這種情況下,你告訴他說學孩子是很喜歡自立的
Self-reliance is different from self-reliance in Europe and the United States
自立跟歐美的自立是不一樣的
because for all parents
因為對所有父母來講
as long as the child wants to read
只要孩子想讀書
I can afford it
我又財務負擔得起
It is my responsibility that you read at the age of 30
你30歲要讀都是我的責任
I think the parents here will probably say Amei
我想這裡面家長們大概都會說阿妹
This has already begun to be completely different from European and American societies.
這就已經開始跟歐美社會完全不一樣
So it's worth our research
所以這就值得我們去研究
Then the localized development model
那麼本土化的發展模式
like we even asked some families about their parenting strategies
就像我們甚至問到一些家庭的教育策略
Last time I also reported to you
上一次我也跟大家報告過
parents will say
父母都會說
Come on, junior high school kids
加油 國三高三的孩子
i don't watch tv
我就不看電視
I don't go out either
我也不出外
I just concentrate on feeding him chicken soup
我就專心的給他補雞湯
But kids don't feel like that
可是小孩子都沒有這樣的感覺
As a child, I feel that my parents have been controlling me
小孩子就感覺父母一直管我
did you talk on the phone
有沒有講電話
have you dated anyone
有沒有跟誰交往
so same problem
所以同樣的問題
You put it on the parents and put it on the child
你放在父母跟放在孩子身上
You can compare the answers when you ask them together.
一起問出來的答案就可以做比較
probably like this
大概是這樣子
That's a long-term follow-up study
那這是一項長期的追蹤研究
At the beginning there were about 5,000 people
一開始大概是五千餘位
noodle shop
面坊
In which we carried out several years later
在這當中我們進行了幾年以後
We feel research
我們覺得調查研究
It seems to give a very important structure
它好像是給一個很重要的架構
But sometimes what everyone wants to see is flesh and blood
可是有的時候大家想要看到的是血肉
This flesh and blood is often what straightforward research can provide
這個血肉就常常是直化研究能夠提供
But if you only do literal research
可是如果你只做直化研究
In fact, what do you represent
其實你代表性是什麼
Everyone often has such a question
大家就常常會有這樣的一個問題
so we are lucky
所以我們很幸運
Some of our more than 5,000 samples can be found
可以從我們五千多個樣本中找到一些
Yeah, do some in-depth interviews with teenagers about the belly.
對 就腹部跟青少年做一些深入訪談
so everyone can see
所以大家可以看到
Our samples are Guo 1 and Guo 3 in 2000
我們樣本是兩千年時國一和國三
The third year of junior high school was the last candidate
當年的國三是最後末代考生
entrance examination system
聯考的制度
Country one is the new system
國一是新的制度
Then I reported to you last time today.
那這裡面今天上次我有跟大家報告
there is a difference
是有差別
We later discovered that under the old system
我們後來就發現在舊制下
It should be said that under the new system
應該這樣講 在新制下
Household income in the top 25%
家庭收入在前25%的
Chances of attending star high schools are remarkably high
上明星高中的機會顯著的高
So it is true that the teaching reform brought some
所以的確教改是帶來一些
greater inequality
更大的不平等
We predict the same
這個我們預測都是一樣的
That first stage is
那第一個階段是
20000 to 2009
20000年到2009年
We started in 1998
我們1998年開始啟動
First bathroom in 1999
1999年第一次做浴室
Then in 2000 a formal investigation was conducted
然後2000年就正式調查
By 2009
到了2009年的時候
They are basically the equivalent of a university
他們基本上就是等於是大學
when you graduated from college
大學畢業的時候
We were all debating whether to continue
我們那時候都在想要不要繼續做
Because I'm getting a little tired
因為開始有一點疲倦了
will be tired
會累
But I didn't expect a phone call to explain the law
可是沒有想到一個電話釋法
It came back very well
竟然回來效果非常好
We agreed to get our spirits up and do it again
我們說好 鼓起精神再來做
Guys, let's take this survey
各位 我們把這個調查
we have a time every friday
我們有一段時間 每個禮拜五
52 weeks a year and at least 40 more weeks
一年52週至少40多週
We are all talking about paper coupons
我們都在討論文券
I brought such a result to Hong Kong
我把這樣的一個成果帶到香港
Bring to Shanghai Bring to Beijing
帶到上海 帶到北京
say unconditionally
說無條件提供
hope you do let us compare
希望你們做 我們來比較
They study the group. After each group discussion,
他們研究小組 團隊每次討論完之後
Let's just say it's a bit difficult. It's too hard.
就說有點困難 這太辛苦了
And then asked me how did you do it
然後反而問我說你們怎麼會做的
I'm just kidding, it's true
我就開玩笑 也是事實
Let me say that you are young and ignorant
我再說年輕不懂事
If you think you can do it, start doing it
覺得可以做就開始做了
Now that I think about it, I'm really happy
那現在回想一下 還真的很高興
There is a group of like-minded friends who have come to this day
有一群志同道合的朋友走到今天
So what about our second phase?
所以我們第二階段呢
adult sample from this time in 2011
從2011年這個時候就是成人樣本
Then we will combine the students from the first country and the third country
那我們就把國一國三的學生合併起來
adult sample
叫做成人樣本
So to put it simply
所以再簡單來講
At that time, we surveyed two groups of samples almost every year
我們那個時候幾乎每年進行兩組樣本的調查
The questions asked by your first-year and third-year students are different
你國一跟國三學生問的問題是不一樣的
Junior high school is different
國三高一又不一樣
So every year we have to design a new topic
所以每年都要設計新的題目
Then at that time add one of the parents
那麼到了那時候還加上父母之一
Also add a tutor
還加導師
you can see
你可以看得到
Then later pooling the adult samples
然後後來合併成人樣本以後
We decided we didn't need to do it every three years
我們就決定不需要每三年做一次就可以
Then you see when the parents started to enter
那你看當年的父母開始進入的時候
Average age 42
平均42歲
at the end of the first phase
第一階段結束的時候
Average age of parents is 52
父母平均是52歲
We are very pleased that Vice President Huang of Zhongyuan Institute
我們非常高興在中原院的黃副院長
with special support
特別支持下
We just sent our IRB to the hospital yesterday
我們是昨天才把我們的IRB送到院方
We were still tweaking our questionnaire last week
我們上禮拜還在調整我們的問卷
This fall we will be
我們今年秋節將要對
Parents with an average age of 62
平均62歲的父母
It's parents who are young and old
就是年輕出老的父母
Do the sixth follow-up survey
做第六次的追蹤調查
Because in their old age
因為在他們出老階段
relationship with acknowledgment of interactions among children
跟承認孩子之間互動的關係
This is not the same as European and American society
這跟歐美社會都不會一樣的
we're not just going to discuss
我們不是只是要探討
Does the concept of school ethics still exist?
校道觀念還是不是存在
school morality
而是校道觀念
is already in your culture
根本就是已經在你的文化中
How do you adjust and perform
你是怎麼樣去調整跟表現
This is the part we are very interested in
這是我們很有興趣的部分
So we basically look like this
所以我們主要是這樣子
Then this is to let everyone know
那這個是讓大家知道
because at this time we say
因為這個時候我們說
We don't know how long we can go
我們不太知道能夠走多久
But for our sociology
可是對我們社會學來講
It's important to be gendered
重要的是要性別成相
social class differences
社會階級的差別
So we believe that this northern Taiwan can
所以我們相信這個北台灣可以
These three places allow us to
這三個地方可以讓我們
to achieve such a purpose
達到這樣的目的
So the sample we start with
所以我們開始的樣本
Probably the structure is like this
大概結構是這樣
Mentor, each of us asks
導師我們每一個都問
One of the parents found out that 70% were mothers
家長之一就發現70%是母親
So we want to catch up with dad this year
所以我們今年想要補補看父親
Would you like to join
願不願意加入
Principal of that country
那國中校長
Later, under the suggestion of Academician Lin Nan
後來在林南院士的建議下
We also supplemented some of their resources
我們也補了他們的一些資源的東西
Here is our sample
這是我們的抽樣
You just believe it must be reliable
你就相信一定是可靠的
And in the end, what is rare for us is
然後最後呢我們難得的是
we sample the whole class
我們全班抽樣
How many do you draw in each class
你在每一班抽幾個
Come out and sample the class
出來跟全班抽樣
different
就不一樣
Because the whole class is sampled you can follow along
因為全班抽樣你可以一路跟隨
they have a relationship between friends
他們有朋友之間的關係
For example, in the last report to you
例如在上一次跟大家報告
in that sometimes good class
在那種有時候好班
Compared with this class with poor grades
跟這個比較成績差的班
Find good students in poor class
發現好學生在成績差的班
more protected
受到比較多的保護
Because these naughty students
因為這些比較調皮搗蛋的學生
will feel that this good student
會覺得這個好學生
to protect a little
要稍微保護一下
but if it is
可是如果是
middle grades
成績中等
Then he gets to medium and he gets affected sometimes
然後他到中等他反而有時候會受到影響
So these are all because you sampled the whole class
所以這些都是因為你全班抽樣
you can see the difference
就可以看到他的差別
So probably the actual answer rate is of course not bad.
所以大概實際回答率當然也不錯
simply speaking
簡單來講
using Western algorithms
用西方的算法
Our response rate should be considered high
我們的回答率應該算是很高的
why 102
為什麼會102
Because we start from scratch every time
因為我們每一次都是從頭
Just start with 5000
就從5000個開始發嘛
Just start from 5000 and start sending from 5000
就從5000個都是從5000個開始發
But the algorithms in the West are all researched by me this year.
可是在西方的算法都是我今年做研究
Just compare with last year and see how much I have left
就是跟去年的比然後看我有剩多少
That's more than 90
那就是90多
so we can even chase this place
所以我們甚至可以追到這個地方
It took a lot of effort to chase after we decided
這是花了很多力氣追完以後我們就決定
ok can continue
好可以繼續做
Then our questionnaire construction is generally comparable
那我們的問卷建構有一般性可比較的
We also have our own feet
也有我們自己的提足
because you want to compare with international
因為你要跟國際做比較
But you have to be like our joint good pressure
可是要自己的像我們這個聯好的壓力
This thing must be designed by yourself.
這個東西一定要自己設計啦
Does anyone have such a topic?
沒有人有這樣的題目嘛
So we will design some of these topics
所以我們就會設計一些這類的題目
Compared with Xixi, they had these ideas about Fengliang's parents when they were young.
你跟西方比從小他們對鳳梁父母這些觀念
is also different
也是不一樣
gender role attitudes
那例如像性別角色態度
Ask once for each stage as we do
像我們的做法就每一個階段問一次
Junior high school, college, adult
國中有高中有大學有大成人有
He is now in his 30s and
他現在30多歲了還有
You can see the change in this little kid from 13 to 31
你可以看到這個小孩子從13歲到31歲的改變
Then his parents asked the exact same question
然後他的父母緣問一模一樣的問題
you can have a vertical comparison
你就可以有個垂直的比較
Parents at the age of 42 and 52
父母在42歲52歲的時候
Will it affect
會不會影響到
kids now
小孩子現在
Okay, so we have some special problems
好 這個就我們有一些特殊的問題
Then I don't know why I thought of doing this in-depth interview
然後我不知道說為什麼會想到要做這個深入訪談
general big plans
一般的大計畫
I remember Germany in 2005
我記得2005年德國
When the National Science Council is about to start their 20,000-person investigation
國科會要開始他們那兩萬人大調查的時候
once invited me to speak
曾經邀我去講
I'll just talk to them
我就跟他們講說
Our planning specially includes the interview of this teammate
我們的規劃特地有這個隊友的訪談
is that we found something
就是我們發現有些東西
you can't quantify
你量化出不來
I remember hearing that they discussed it for half a year
我記得當時聽說後來他們討論了半年
because their psychologists would love to
因為他們的心理學家很想做
But then other scholars decided that it was too difficult
可是後來其他的學者決定說這個太困難
they just give up
他們就放棄
So I'm glad we still made it
所以我很高興我們還是做出來
like in retrospect
像回想起來那時候
how long is this
這多少時候
As long as the door tells us he's free
只要樣門跟我們說他有空
Manage what time the ends of the earth
管理天涯海角什麼時間
we all cooperate
我們全部都配合
Then two teachers and two assistants went to visit respectively
然後就兩個老師在兩個助理分別去訪問
Then look at some of their situations
然後看他們的一些情況
I still remember that time when we saw this girl from Beibei
我還記得那個時候我們看到有這個北女的學生
parents will tell us
父母會跟我們說
The 50,000 yuan we discussed in the end
這五萬塊我們討論了最後
Buying her a computer won't repair that roof
給她買電腦就不修那個屋簷了
Later, he went to the medical department of the National Defense Medical Academy.
後來上了國防醫學院的醫學系
we are really very happy
我們真的是非常高興
Well, we've published straight talk research
那麼我們已經出版的直話的研究
Also tell us that between parents and children
也跟我們說父母跟孩子之間
Correspondence
關聯一致
When the expectations for future education are the same
對未來教育期望目標一致的時候
Of course it is best for children to learn
對小孩子的學習當然是最好
so this is
所以這個是
The month we discussed in the basement of the Mingzhi Institute
當年我們在明知所地下室討論的一個月
Because everyone wants more samples for their questions
因為每個人都希望自己的題目有更多的樣本
that won't work
那是不行的
must be fair
一定要公平
So we use various methods
所以我們就用各種各樣的方法
find these 60 pairs
找出這60對
so really being
所以真的被
What are you doing today if there is an interviewee
今天在做的如果有受訪者
we really appreciate you
我們真是謝謝你
Because we didn't draw randomly
因為我們不是隨便抽的
I draw you out according to the rules
都是照規矩抽出你來
And you promise you think how happy we are
然後你答應你想我們有多高興
That's the first phase of the research structure
那這是第一階段的研究架構
I also reported it last time
我上回也報告過了
Simply put, someone said
那簡單來說有人我說
What are your main findings in Phase 1?
你第一階段主要發現是什麼
I said if you really want to talk
我說如果真的要講
We're going to study homeschool community interactions
我們要研究家庭學校社區的交互作用
As found in many of our papers
就我們很多論文發現
Early family experiences do have long-term effects
早期家庭經驗的確會產生長期的影響
For example we have 40% look like
例如我們有40%的樣子
He actually lived with his grandparents for a while before he was 12.
他其實在12歲以前曾經跟祖父母有住過一段時間的
Three generations living under one roof
三代同堂的經驗
Let him now have a more positive evaluation in terms of intergenerational relations
讓他現在在代間關係上看有比較正面的評價
but the interesting thing is
可是有趣的是
If you live with your grandparents
如果是跟外公外婆合住的
He has negative feelings towards his father
他對爸爸的感情比較負面
I still remember that time
我還記得那時候
The editor-in-chief of Xigan in the United States has been asking me to explain this
美國的席竿的主編一直要我解釋這個
I said we haven't had a straight talk yet, what should I say?
我說我們就還沒有去做直話我怎麼講
I said we could give us a Cruel
我說我們可以給我們一個Cruel
That is to say, whatever you are in society
就是說你凡是你在社會上
Use a non-traditional atypical living arrangement
用一個非傳統非典型的居住安排
Actually everyone
其實每一個人
The parties involved are aware of this situation
當事人都知道這個情況
So when you encounter non-traditional atypical
所以當你遇到非傳統非典型的時候
It's not actually in your best interest
其實對你來說並不是最有利的
But I remember we explained it like this
但是我記得我們是這樣解釋
Then the education diversion I will talk about later
那麼教育分流我等會會說
Then Leaving Home and Education also published some articles
那離家跟教育也出了一些文章
We found Sakuro
我們發現章郎
The children in Yilan have the most experience away from home
宜蘭的小孩子他離家的經驗是最多的
This is true for employment and education
為了就業為了就學的確是如此
Then why start the second
那為什麼開啟第二份
We say after teens turn 22
我們說青少年到了22歲之後
he enters early adulthood
他進入成年初期
this experience
這個經驗
And recently this one is prone to cough when talking a lot
而且最近這個在講話多了就容易咳嗽
no matter what
不論如何
This You Track Teen Experiences Into Early Adulthood
這個你追蹤青少年進入成年初期的經驗
you don't use backtracking
你不要用回溯的
It's important that you master it right now
你就是當下就掌握它是很重要
And because we've had from middle school to early adulthood
而且因為我們已經有從國中高中成年初期
mid term
中期
So it will have different life stages which links
所以它就會有不同生命階段是哪些連結
We all have some important factors to look at
我們都有一些重要的因素可以看
In addition, you compare the differences between the parent and child generations
此外你比較親子兩代之間的差異
We don't seem to be doing a good job at the moment.
目前我們好像還沒有好好地做到哪方面
But this is where this material can be invaluable
可是這是這份資料可以提供寶貴的地方
So the second stage samples are simply
所以第二階段樣本簡單來講
We have a sample of ordinary people and we have conducted a total of three waves of surveys
我們有常人樣本我們一共進行過三波調查
2011 14 and 17 we all start in October every year
2011 14和17我們都是每一年的10月開始
so every other year
所以都會做到隔年
As a result, after returning in 11 years, I got the materials in 12 years
結果11年回來以後12年拿到資料
We found that 7% are married
我們發現7%結婚了
I remember at that time my heart moved
我記得那時候我就心裡一動
Wow, if the spouse survey can be done at this time
哇如果這個時候可以把配偶調查做起來
It's like the beginning of his family formation
就等於是他家庭組成一開始
we collect data
我們就收集資料
how precious it is
這是多麼樣的寶貴
I still remember that time our group had a little discussion
我還記得那時候我們小組還稍微討論了一下
Professor Zhang Yinghua is still in our advisory committee, and the report says
張應華教授還在我們諮詢委員說報告說
According to the boss
依老闆說
just have to do
就是一定要做
It's like saying I must buy that dress
好像說我一定要買那件衣服一樣
I still think my mother is joking
我還想我媽開玩笑
Sorry for the recording today
抱歉今天有錄音錄影
I speak well
我好好講話
Come
來
So our first wave of spouse surveys
所以我們那時候第一波配偶調查
After the decision in 2012, we will implement it in 2013
2012年決定以後我們2013就執行
Then from the second wave, we will implement it in the second year
那從此第二波我們就第二年執行
The third wave of investigations was completed last year.
那第三波調查就是去年已經完成
So let's put it simply
所以我們簡單來講
if you forget later
待會你要是忘記一下
7% here are married
這裡有7%結婚了
Average age 25
平均25歲
19% to 20% here are married
這裡有19%到20%結婚了
Average age 28
平均28歲
In this third wave of surveys, there are more than 39%
就這個第三波調查有39%點多
almost 40
快要40
This is consistent with our government statistics
這個跟我們政府的統計數據一致的
so we are happy
所以我們很高興
I won't talk about this
這個我就不講了
we have some topics that are different
我們有一些題目是不一樣
Simply put, what I just said
那簡單來說就剛剛我講的
Now probably won't be able to make it to 40
現在很可能沒辦法做到40歲
if not
否則的話
40-year-old parents and 40-year-old teenagers
父母40歲跟青少年40歲
the whole vertical metaphor
整個的垂直比喻
that is really necessary
那是真的很不得不
amazing thing
很不得了的事情
I hope some of our colleagues here are willing to take the list
希望我們在座同仁有人願意接榜
hehehehe
呵呵呵呵
good
好
Collect the whole data and look
整個資料收集一下看起來
wow, really powerful
哇 實在是很有力氣
Probably all that I just reported to you
大概就是所有我剛剛跟各位報告
It's all on this list
都在這個單子上面了
I take it apart
我把它分開來看
first stage
第一個階段
You can see that I put the net reverse rate
你可以看到我把網反率
write on it
寫在上面
Everyone should know that when they were in middle school
大家要知道他們在國中時期
We are ballpoint pens, aren't we?
我們是原子筆一根是不是
Because our funds have always been consolidated
因為我們經費一直很結聚
I'm sorry, at that time, it was really fundraising.
抱歉喔 那時候是真的經費結聚
Later, after funding
後來有了經費以後
We also give two hundred Taiwan dollars
我們也是給兩百塊台幣
what about the money
那這個錢呢
I found the West and exchanged it for US dollars
我找到西方是換成美金
I'm a little embarrassed
我都有點不好意思
But I don't think it's okay
不過我覺得沒關係
this meaningful thing
這個這個有意義的事
Doesn't necessarily require a lot of resources
也不見得要很多的資源
we just try to do it
我們努力去做就是了
so so probably
那麼所以大概是這樣
The second stage can be seen
第二階段大家可以看得到
we started
我們一開始
All are from the original more than 5,000
通通是從原來的五千多位
but remember
可是要記住
It was already the tenth wave and the eleventh wave.
那時候已經是第十波 第十一波了
when the past nine waves
當過去的九波
many people don't answer
有很多人是不回答
he just jumps
他就跳
Jumped out, I just talked about 60 or so, some 30 or so jumped out
跳出去了嘛,剛剛講60幾,有30幾跳出去了
We still try our best to ask these people
那這些人我們還是拼著命去問
If the visitor says you have to knock on the door three times, it will be counted.
要訪人說要敲門三次,才可以算
No, so this stressful time is too much for the interviewer
不要,所以對訪人來說這個壓力時代太大
Every time we do a survey, we get some
我們每一次做完調查就會接到一些
complaint letter
抱怨性函
i mean please
就是說拜託你們
I'm not good at English, when did you want to talk like this?
英文不善啦,你什麼時候才要這樣就這一類的話
We used to ask Mr. Zhang Honghua
我們以前都是拜託張宏華老師
The reply letter of the eight tails of the video, in fact, let’s talk about it
視頻八尾的回信,其實講一講去
Just a word, we do academic research, we will continue to come
就是一句話,我們做學術研究,我們會繼續來
On the contrary, let me dismiss your intention
反倒,打消你的意思啦
Later, after discussion, everyone said that this thing is not very fair to visitors.
那後來大家討論以後說,這個東西對訪人不是很公平
So we put those that are no longer there
所以我們把那些其實已經不在
And it has already clearly stated the people he interviewed in the drama
而且已經很明確講說他劇訪的人
After removing him, we'll do it all over again
把他去掉以後,我們再重新來做
Then you can see that the second wave has better results
然後你就可以看得到,第二波就有比較好的結果
Then the third wave had better results
然後第三波有更好的結果
During the same time period, we conduct interviews
同樣的時間內,我們執行訪談
keep track, the original
持續追蹤,原來的
Fifty one, sixty, keep chasing, chasing until now
五十一位,六十位,一直追,追到現在
Seventeen are still in there and no one else
有十七位還在裏頭,不是其他人
we don't want to
我們不願意了
And partly because
而一部分原因也是因為
The focus of our interview has changed slightly
我們訪談的重點稍微有點改變
i will say
我都會會說
So simply say for example
所以簡單來講例如
Qualitative research has 22
直話研究有22位
i want to thank you very much
我要特別謝謝你
I don't know how many of you
我不知道你們當中有幾位
We have visited four waves
已經被我們訪問過四波
The third and fourth waves begin
第三第四波開始
We don't have to go to Yilan
我們就不用去宜蘭了
They came to us on a motorcycle
他們騎個摩托車來找我們了
This is really different
這個真的是不太一樣
But I really went to Yilan
可是真的去宜蘭的
i still remember our assistant
我還記得我們的助理
When I go to Yilan to visit
在我去宜蘭去訪問
the next car
下的那個車
i saw him lick ken
我看到他舔墾
I just remember that man's house was there
我就記得那個人的家在那裡
He said teacher how do you know
他說老師你怎麼知道
I say because of the interviewee
我說因為那個受訪者
let me dove twice
放了我兩次鴿子
so i know exactly where his house is
所以我非常清楚他家在哪裡
things like this
像這一類的事情
just look at him
就看著他
in the same class
當年在同班
children in class together
一起上課的小孩子
now some will be in
現在有的要在
fishing port to visit him
漁港去訪問他
Some cook clear soup in the west
有的在西部做清湯駕
Some dads call and say
有的爸爸打電話來說
He is studying abroad for a Ph.D.
他出國在念博士
come back later
以後再回來
this is what we talk about
這就是我們講的
Multiple Growth Trajectories
多元的成長軌跡
in my heart
我心裡是
Feeling
有感觸的
Then we will continue to visit in the future
那我們未來還會繼續訪問
Simply put, we want to visit 20 unmarried
簡單來講我們希望訪問20個未婚的
40 married
40個已婚的
In this regard, we also ask Dr. Yuan Yongzhen for help.
這方面我們也是請袁詠珍博士幫忙
Then enter today's topic
那接下來才進入今天的主題
pretty much what i said
跟我講的差不多
I also want to talk about the front for half an hour
我也想說半小時講前面
I'm going to talk about the long-term effects of family experience.
那我要講家庭經驗長期影響
Long-term effects of educational diversion and educational achievement
教育分流和教育成就的長期影響
and the marriage and childbearing of the current young generation
以及當前年輕世代的婚姻與生育
Our topic is called Zhuan Daren
我們這個題目叫轉大人
So I must tell you what it means to become an adult.
所以一定要跟大家講一下什麼是轉大人
So I added it this morning
所以我今天早上把它加進去
If you transfer to an adult, it is usually in academic research
轉大人的話一般在學術研究上
oldest this this this this
最古老的這個這個這個這個
Usage This is Professor Shi Dalin Ruping
用法這個是施大林如平教授
He finished an article he gave us later
他做完後面他的他給我們的一篇文章
Probably finish school and find a job
大概是完成學業找到工作
Get married, have a family, have children, etc.
結婚成家生育子女等等
But Zhuan adults are one
但是轉大人是一個
objective
客觀的
or subjective determination
還是主觀的認定
did you say
有沒有說
When you are eighteen, you will be an adult
到十八歲來個成年你
you become an adult
你就變成大人了
what about things like this
像這一類的事情怎麼看
what about now
那現在呢
There are some called big three
有一些叫做big three
you are responsible
你自己負責任
make your own decisions
自己獨立做決定
economically independent
經濟上自己獨立
to be honest
坦白講
This is the same as the old indicator
這跟古老的這個指標來講
that is more difficult to measure
那個比較困難測量
Yes or no
是不是
what do you mean by making your own decision
你什麼叫做自己做決定
own responsibility
自己負責任
This is relatively simple
這個是比較簡單的
But everyone thinks this is not enough
可是大家覺得這個不能滿足
because they think this thing
因為他們覺得這個東西
is a subjective determination
是一個主觀認定
He needs some objective indicators
他要有一些的客觀的指標
to match him
來配合他
so we just
所以我們就
use this scale
用這個量本
Then we made a scale
然後我們就做了一個量表
This scale is mainly based on Western
這個量表主要是參考西方
The adult scale they made
他們做的轉大人的量表
But we will also cooperate
可是我們也會配合
Our own Taiwan special
我們自己台灣特殊的
social context
社會脈絡
For example, wind foster parents to parents before
例如風養父母給父母前
This is probably the West
這個大概西方
there will be no such topic
不會有這樣的題目
Then the result
然後結果呢
The discovery can be divided into two major
發現可以分成兩個大部分
One is a mature personality
一個是人格方面成熟
Will you wait for others
你會不會為人想等等
One is social role transformation
一個是社會角色轉型
It is more like the traditional one just mentioned earlier.
就是比較像那個剛剛前面講的傳統的
As a result you can see
結果你可以看得到
What men and women say
男性跟女性來講的話
Personality Maturity Vs Social Transformation
人格成熟度比社會轉型
more recognized
更得到認可
it has a higher score
它分數比較高
Is there more than 4 o'clock and more than 3 o'clock?
有沒有 這個4點多 這個3點多
Then
然後
This indicator is also the same as that of Western studies
這個指標跟西方研究也是相同的
Interestingly, males are more
有趣的是男性比女性
Greater recognition of the norms of social norms
更認可社會規範的準則
simply speaking
簡單來講
from the 1970s
從1970年代開始
research on attitudes towards gender roles
做性別角色的態度研究以降
There are two results that have not changed until now
有兩個到至今都沒有改變的結果
And it's the same all over the world
而且是全世界都一樣
First, men are more conservative than women
第一個 男性比女性更保守
more traditional
更傳統
The second highly educated
第二個 教育程度高的
less educated than
比教育程度低的
less conservative
更不保守
probably these two
大概這兩個
whatever you do it won't change
隨便你怎麼做都不會改變
We study in Taiwan
我們在台灣研究中
There are three unfilial
有那個不孝有三
After Empress Wu was great, she must give birth
武後偉大就一定要生育的
son's study also vent so
兒子的研究 也發洩如此
And after the fertility rate drops
而且生育率降低之後
This is even more so
這個更是如此
Originally, with the development of society
本來這種隨著社會的發展
This concept should go all the way down
這種概念應該一路一路下降
But when we were in 2008
可是當我們2008年
when you have a problem
遇到問題的時候
it rises immediately
它馬上就上升
So the general public
所以民眾的一般
the answer is quite rational
回答是相當理性的
We really want to trust everyone's answers
我們真的要信任大家的回答
good
好
Then the long-term impact of family structure
那麼家庭結構長期影響
There are many teachers in our group
在我們小組中有許多的老師
Including Mr. Zhong Yuhui present here, etc.
包括在座的中 育慧老師等等
are here for a long time
都長期在座
I think I'll tell you something here
我想這裡我跟大家講一下
family experiences we care about
家庭經驗我們在乎的是
a structure a relationship
一個結構 一個關係
what is its long-term effect
它的長期效果是怎麼樣
Then because I'm on the summary
然後因為我在摘要上
There is a special mention of parental divorce
有特別講到父母離婚
What is the impact on the children
到底對子女的影響又是什麼
Then I will give you a report here
那在這裡我跟大家做一個報告
Let's use a sample from this country to see
我們用這個國一樣本來看
In 2000, the first year of the National
2000年國一的時候
both his parents
他雙親都在
No divorce is 87
就沒有離婚的是87
At the age of 22, it changed to 83.5
到了22歲的時候變83.5
At the age of 31, change
到了31歲的時候變
75.2 Why?
75.2 为什么呢
This is a divorce or separation
这个是离婚或分居
did you see
你看到没有
increase 0.5 0.5
增加0.5 0.5
probably not that much
大概不是那么多
but one of the parents died
可是父母之一死亡的
increased a lot
就增加很多了
So among today's 31-year-old adults
所以到今天31岁的成人中
we will see
我们会看到
about a quarter
大概有四分之一
Not all parents are together
并不是父母都一起在一起的
So the family structure changes
所以家庭结构改变
if you want to do research
如果要做研究
You are divided into two-parent families and non-two-parent families
你就分成双亲家庭跟非双亲家庭
about what i said
就大概我讲的
about three quarters
大概是三四分之一
This thing is most related to blunt
这个东西最blunt一些关联
you can see
就可以看得到
College Graduation for Two-Parent Families
双亲家庭的大学毕业
The ratio is relatively high, right?
比例比较高对不对
Those who graduated from high school in non-parental families
非双亲家庭高中职毕业的
relatively high ratio
比例比较高
So there are some differences in education level
所以这里面就有一些教育程度的差异
then i will talk next
那我接下来讲
I start from the family structure and family relationship
我就从家庭结构家人关系
Impact on Adolescents' Journeys
对青少年者的历程的影响
I'll jump off us first
我先跳开我们
PYP shows you how our population structure has changed
PYP 給大家看一下我們人口結構的變遷
The problem of declining birthrate and aging population
少子化人口老化的問題
And then from the parental divorce what we call the incomplete family upbringing
然後從父母離婚這種我們叫做非完整家庭的成長背景
To observe the development of intimate relationships and family formation in adulthood
來觀察成年後親密關係的發展與家庭的組成
this piece
這張
This is the number of children born
這個是生育的子女的數目
You can see that in 1976 we had 420,000 births in Taiwan
你可以看得到1976年我們台灣生了42萬
The lowest time was only 160,000
最低的時候只有16萬
180,000 were born last year
那去年生了18萬
So our fertility rate is declining very fast
所以我們的生育率是下降的非常的快
The red ones tell you that this is the fertility rate
紅色的是告訴你這是生育率
down like this
就這樣一路下降來
then why
那為什麼呢
you can see
你可以看得到
As long as it is a farming year, the fertility rate must increase
只要是農年生育率一定提高
All the way down, there will be a high wind in the agricultural year
一路下降一到農年就會有一個高風
This is how I see cultural norms from this graph
這就是我從這張圖看到文化規範
This thing that never dies
不死不死的這個東西
That
那
Taiwan is very important
台灣很重要是這樣
Do you see the lonely year
孤欄年看到沒有
Marriage rate dropped from 6.5 to 5
出結婚率從6.5降到5
don't get married
不要結婚
Year of the Tiger
虎年的時候
That's when our Taiwan had the lowest birth rate in the world
就是當年我們台灣是全世界最低的出生率
Because people don't want to have children
因為大家不要生孩子
the government is very worried
政府非常擔心
Fortunately, the next year is the 100th year of the Republic of China, advertising everywhere
還好次年是民國百年到處做廣告
Originally a hundred years and what a hundred years
原本百年好和百年什麼
A hundred years of harmony is not enough
單單百年好和還不夠
The second year is the Year of the Dragon
第二年又是個龍年
that all the parents are trying to do
那所有的父母都謀逐的盡
if the children have a spouse
如果孩子們有配偶的
get married quickly
趕快去結婚
I just hope to give birth to a dragon son or a dragon girl.
就希望生個龍子或龍女也可以了
you can see
你可以看到
Year of the Dragon jumps so high in the second year
第二年龍年跳這麼高
But now it's slowly falling
可是現在又慢慢的下降來了
if you look at this
如果你看這張
you can see the divorce rate
你可以看到離婚率
It's probably leveled off.
其實大概已經變平坦了
So the marriage rate goes up and down
那麼這個結婚率上上下下
Only a hundred years of happiness and birth
只有百年好和生下
then came down again
然後又降下來了
but this
可是這個
As long as it is the Year of the Tiger
只要是虎年一定降
as long as it is the year of the dragon
只要是龍年
Must be born
一定生
So you're in a downward spiral
所以你在一片往下降當中
When you meet the Year of the Dragon, give birth
遇到龍年就生一下
we are in such a society
我們是處在這樣的社會
I just want to share with you
我就是等於跟大家分享
The influence of cultural norms
文化規範的影響
sometimes you don't even have to ask
你有時候根本不用去問你
agree or disagree he is here
同不同意他就在這裡
he is like this
他就是這個樣子
So in terms of unmarried men and women in Taiwan
那麼以台灣男女未婚率來講的話
everyone can see
大家可以看得到
Of course, the unmarried rate of women is high
當然還是女的未婚率高
But it's quite high
不過也是相當的高
So back to our own research
所以回到我們自己的研究
Let's talk about whether the family structure has any influence
我們就說家庭結構有沒有什麼影響
we know low birth rates
我們知道低生率
this problem is serious
這個問題很嚴重
And the phenomenon of marriage metaphor package
而且婚喻包裹的現象
It means that the society still does not accept out-of-wedlock children
意思就是社會還是不接受未婚生子
I remember when I was doing an interview
我記得我做一個訪談的時候
He said that the unmarried pregnant interviewee
他說這個未婚懷孕的受訪者
Tell me he doesn't even want to marry him
跟我說他其實都不想嫁給他
Because he thinks he can't get along with him and doesn't love each other
因為他覺得他跟他合不來不相愛
Parents say I don't care if you love each other or not
父母說我不管你相不相愛
you hurry to get married
你趕快去結婚
divorce after childbirth
生完孩子要離婚再離婚
Then I think hey, yes
那我覺得 哎 對齁
This is the wedding package we've been talking about
這就是我們一直在講的婚禦包裹嘛
child to be born in marriage
孩子要出生在婚姻中
this is very important
這是非常重要的
so what
所以呢
Why Young People Lack Motivation to Marry and Have Children
為什麼年輕人缺乏結婚生育動機
this is what everyone is asking
這大家都在問
Let's start with family experience
我們先從家庭經驗著手
In particular our data allow us to explore from early experience
尤其我們的資料允許我們從早期的經驗去探討
then speaking
那麼來講
Early Family Experiences for Adolescents
青少年早期家庭經驗
Regardless of childhood and adolescence
不管兒童期青少年期
Are the parents divorced?
父母有沒有離婚
In many Chinese families, the parents do not divorce
我們中國家庭很多是父母不離婚
but conflicting
可是有衝突的
complete family
在西方叫完整家庭
We also call it a complete family here.
我們這邊也是叫完整家庭
But what if we add a disguise?
可是如果加一個變相進去呢
parent-child conflict
還有親子關係衝突
Early experiences of adolescence
青少年期的早期經驗
Dating Behavior in Your Early Adulthood
對你成年初期的約會行為
what are the marriage expectations
婚姻期望是如何
especially in your 30s
尤其到了30多歲
We can talk about the actual act of marriage
我們可以講到實際的婚姻行為
Everyone here should know
大家在座應該也知道
Because newspapers and magazines often say
因為報章雜誌常說
The average age of marriage in Taiwan
我們台灣現在出婚平均年齡
Probably male 32 years old
大概是男生32歲
30 years old girl
女生30歲
So we also say that our data is just right
所以我們也說我們這個資料剛好就是可以
react to such a situation
反應這樣的一個情況
I can only speak quickly
我這只能快快地講
Generally speaking, the situation of children under divorced parents will tell you
父母離婚下的子女處境一般來講會跟你說
His self-esteem comes first
他自尊第一
bad grades wait
成績不好等等
negative impact
負面衝擊
And often tell you it will last into adulthood
而且常常跟你說會延續到成年期
However, it is uncertain in the literature that
可是文獻上不確定的是
After parents divorce, children are less likely to want to marry
父母離婚之後孩子是比較不想結婚
Or get married early
還是反而提早結婚
Because if a child doesn't want to marry it's because he sees conflict
因為孩子如果不想結婚是因為他看到衝突
Seeing that the parent-child relationship is not good
看到父母親子關係不好
But some marry early because he thinks he needs a
可是有些提早結婚是因為他覺得他需要一個
relation
關係
He comes from a place where resources are relatively scarce
他來自資源比較缺乏的地方
He needs to get into marriage
他需要一進入婚姻
So this is the one we want to know
所以這個是我們想要知道的一個
The topic of the research is as follows
研究的題目這樣講
so what
所以呢
We climb points complete family divorced family
我們爬分完整家庭離婚家庭
We pay special attention to this divorced family
這個離婚家庭我們特別著重
when he got divorced
他離婚的時間點
Before 13 or 12
是13歲之前還是12歲
12, Stan's Upper or Under 12
12歲,斯坦的上或12歲以下
Then full family, we join a cumulative conflict
然後完整家庭,我們加入一個累積的衝突
go see the difference
去看看有什麼不一樣
We want the explanation to be him
我們希望解釋就是他
Dating Behavior in Early Adulthood, Late Adolescence and His Marriage Expectations
成年初期,青少年晚期的約會行為跟他的婚姻期望
That's when you're 19 to 20 years old
就是19到20歲的時候
simply speaking
簡單來講
As you can see, let's say it's a two-parent family
你可以看得到,假設是雙親家庭
Probably this ratio
大概是這樣的比例
But my parents divorced when I was in elementary school
可是父母在兒童期小學的時候離婚的
How is he, compared to 13 years old
他怎麼樣,他跟13歲來比的話
After the age of 13, the parents experience the divorce of their parents
13歲以後,父母經驗到父母離婚的
He has relatively no marriage expectations, he won't say he wants to get married
他比較沒有婚姻期望,他不會說他想結婚
But before the age of 12, there are more dating partners
可是12歲以前的呢,比較有約會對象
and the number of people who are dating
而且有約會的人數
He is more interested in the development of intimacy, so let's talk about it
他比較熱衷於親密關係的發展,這樣子講好了
What about parental conflict?
那父母關係衝突高的呢
He acted like the one whose parents divorced after the age of 13
他表現得很像13歲後父母離婚的
that that category
那個那個那個類別
So in addition, we also found in this study
所以另外我們也這個研究中也發現
It can be seen that the sense of attachment between parents and children is very important
可以看到親子間的依附感是很重要的
If you compare your relationship with your father
你如果跟父親關係比
good words you are less likely to say
很好的話你比較不會說
we have marriage expectations
我們有婚姻的期望
Divorce if your child wife and parents
如果你兒童妻父母就離婚
But if you have a good relationship with your mother
可是你跟母親關係很好的話
You also have less expectation of marriage
你也比較不會有婚姻的期望
In other words, everyone can hear
換句話說大家可以聽得到
Divorce or not is a family structure
離婚與否是一個家庭結構
But you are in a divorced family structure
可是你在離婚的家庭結構中
relationship with parents family relationship
跟父母之間的關係 家人關係
can have some harmonizing effect
可以有一些調和的效果
like this
這樣子講
So if you're with a two-parent family
所以如果你跟雙親家庭
And the group with low conflict
而且衝突低的這一組來比
Parents' Early Divorce Experience
父母早期離婚經驗
lead to young adulthood
會導致年輕成年期
Negative effects of intimacy
親密關係的負面影響
So sometimes I have been busy for a year and a half
所以有時候忙了一年半年
Everyone just got this sentence
大家就只得到這一句
Everyone listened in one go
大家一下就聽完了
well then
好 那麼
adult children
到了成年子女
We found from 201114
我們就從201114發現
It's strange, parents can't get divorced
奇怪喔 父母離不離婚
It has little to do with his actual marriage
跟他實際婚姻關係關聯不大
Definitely a two-parent family
確定的是雙親家庭
Grown children are less likely to seek marriage
長大的孩子比較不可能找婚
probably so
大概是這樣
so we say what to do
所以我們說怎麼辦
Okay, let's guess step by step. Don't worry.
好 我們一步一步來猜 不要急
Let's first invite Professor Dai Cuier from Taipei University
我們先請台北大學戴翠兒教授
For the 7% of 25-year-olds who were married in 2011
針對2011年25歲已經結婚的那百分之七
let's see what's going on
來看看到底是怎麼回事
literature tells us
文獻上告訴我們
Families High in Conflict Have Lower Marriage Expectations
衝突高的家庭有較低的婚姻期望
Does that mean you're less likely to seek marriage when you're 25?
是否表示你25歲的時候比較不可能找婚呢
Well, after he made various arrangements,
那麼他在做了各種整理之後
I'll show you first
我先給大家看一下
we are probably like this now
我們現在大概是這樣
These married people we DIP married people
這些已婚者 我們DIP已婚者
This is probably the case
大概是這樣的情況
He has fathered children quite tall
他已經生育子女的相當的高
In other words, marriage and childbirth are a package
換句話說婚育是個包裹
He's getting married, he's really going to have kids
他要結婚他真的就是要生小孩
but give birth within seven months of marriage
可是婚後七個月內生育
I do not include those born before marriage
我不包括婚前就生育的
So this pre-marriage
所以這個婚前
For example this is 52%
例如這個是52%
at the age of 25
25歲的時候
What is it called?
叫什麼 奉子命成婚
In fact, not only 52%
其實不只52%
Because 89% of you are already born
因為你還有89%是已經孩子生出來了
you can say it like this
可以這樣子講
Then we also ask by the way
然後我們也順便問一下
But when you're 28 or 31, it's more normal, right?
可是到了28 31歲就比較正常了是不是
Then you can see
然後可以看到
contemporary young couple
當代年輕夫妻
These are all under 32
這都是32歲以下
The average ratio of living with parents is quite high
平均跟父母同住的比率是相當高的
This is of course related to economic resources
這當然跟經濟資源有關
This is absolutely different from European and American countries.
這也是絕對跟歐美國家不一樣的地方
Taiwan is in the middle of East Asia
台灣在整個東亞當中
It has always been relatively similar to the Korean model.
跟韓國的模式一向是比較相近的
But I don't know if they have such information
可是我不知道他們有沒有這樣的資料
then you can see
那你可以看得到
On one side of the island, the husband and the parents are the main ones
島一邊都是跟夫方父母為主
There will be no fewer than Qifang's parents
跟七方父母不會比較少
good
好
Professor Dai Xuwei and others
戴徐維教授等
He said I'd first look at pregnancy before marriage
他說我先看婚前懷孕以後
I found out my parents divorced when I was 13
就發現父母在13歲時候離婚的
more likely to lead to premarital pregnancy
的確比較可能會導致婚前懷孕
You have cohabitation and premarital sexual experience
你有同居有婚前性經驗的
possible
可能
So what about early marriage, will you find out that your parents are divorced and gone?
那麼早婚呢 你到底會不會發現父母離婚不見了
But this thing came out
可是這個東西出來了
In other words, this is called the family structure
換句話說 這個叫做家庭結構
this is called family relationship
這個叫做家庭關係
And in this relationship, parent-child conflict is high
而且這個關係當中 親子間衝突高的
He is more likely to marry early
他比較可能早婚
But seeing the conflict between parents
可是看到父母之間在衝突的
Less likely to get married but not to marry early
比較不想結婚 但不會早婚
So in adolescence, it's very similar to what I just said earlier.
所以在青少年期 跟前面剛剛那講的就很像
Adolescent Witnessing Parents Arguing
青少年期目睹父母爭吵
and divorced parents will reduce his desire to marry
以及父母離婚的 會降低他結婚的慾望
But if there is a conflict between parents and children
可是如果是親子之間有衝突的話
Instead he hurried to get married
他反而趕快去結婚
So in this study
所以以這個研究來講
If parents divorced before the age of 13
父母在13歲之前離婚的話
Will affect pre-marital pregnancy of children
會影響子女婚前的懷孕
But it won't affect your early marriage
但是不會影響你的早婚
Early adolescence, high parental conflict will not marry early
青少年初期 父母衝突高不會早婚
High parent-child conflict leads to early marriage, it's clear
親子衝突高會早婚 就很清楚了嘛
But those with cohabitation and premarital relationships are also more likely to marry early
但有同居和婚前關係的早婚可能性也高
Is that clear?
這樣講清楚嗎?
I'm very hardworking
我很努力
To put it simply, there is a marriage package phenomenon
簡單來說,這裡有一個婚禦包裹的現象
You said that between cultural norms and economic change
你說在文化規範跟經濟改變當中
This level of tension is a characteristic of Chinese society
這種緊張程度,這是一個華人社會特色
The parcels of the marriage between generations are all in this place
代間的同住婚禦的包裹都是在這個地方
However, Western studies often talk about an economic capacity
可是西方研究常常就會談到一個經濟能力
something that affects you a lot that we're just going to observe
影響你很多的我們剛剛要觀察的東西
But economic ability, they found that it is beneficial to men
可是經濟能力,他們發現對男性是有
The effect of living in different places has contributed
異住的效果,有貢獻
Contribute to him to get married, but it is the opposite for girls
貢獻他去結婚,對女生反而相反
Girls who have high financial ability are less likely to think that they are married
女生如果經濟能力高,比較沒有認為有結婚的
hope and desire
希望跟慾望
so so we say ok , let's look at 28 years old
那麼所以我們就說好,那我們就看看28歲
during the second wave
第二波的時候
What's the problem, 25 years old
有些什麼問題,25歲
I think if you call him an early marriage, no one will have a problem
我想你叫他早婚,不會有人有意見
Because he obeyed his son's order to get married, that's why
因為他奉子命成婚,也是他的原因
Well, at the age of 28, just now he is slowly approaching normal
那麼28歲呢,剛剛他慢慢趨近於正常了
So Ma Guoxun
所以馬國勳
Professor Ma Guoxun, I am asking this question
馬國勳教授哥我就在問這個問題
I think what's the reason you got married and got out of prison?
我想你出婚出獄的因素是什麼
is there any difference
有沒有差異
I'll go faster here
這裡我會走快一點
I just let everyone know we're not kidding
我只讓大家知道我們不是開玩笑
we really take it seriously
我們真的認真做
Especially our Vice President Huang
尤其我們這個黃副院長
is our funding
是我們的funding的
we need to tell him
我們要講給他聽
look at
你看看
there is a recording for today
對今天有錄音
this structural factor
這個結構性因素
Normative factors
規範性因素
relational factors
關係性因素
I just said that structure is a resource
我剛已經講了結構是一種資源
relationship is also a resource
關係也是一種資源
This is the big trend
這是巨勢面向
it's interpersonal
這是人際之間關係的
The other is cultural norms
另外一個是文化規範
Then generally do it, of course it depends on whether you are learning
然後一般做當然會看你自己是不是在學
Is there a job?
是不是有工作嘛
fine human ability
人精細能力有關
Then we use the survey of the main book
然後我們就用主要本的調查
All the way from 16 years old to 20 to 30 years old
一路從16歲看到20 30歲
Then use the first two waves of spouse surveys
然後再用前兩波配偶調查
Then use this model to do
然後用這個模型去做
What we're trying to explain is the age of marriage
我們要解釋的就是出婚年齡
with the age of release from prison
跟出獄的年齡
analysis in disguise
就分析變相
e.g. structural disguise
例如結構性變相
we used where are you
我們就用了你在哪裡
Parents' Education Achievement Family Income
父母教育成就家庭收入
relatively large
比較巨式的
normative attitude
那麼像規範態度
gender role attitudes
我們就會有性別角色態度
what traditional family values
什麼傳統家庭價值
in terms of family relations
而家庭關係方面
We used negative parent-child conflict
我們用了負面的親子衝突
positive family ties
正面的家庭連結
These are the constitution
這些都是體質
Then we add another question
然後我們另外加一題
when i was fifteen
十五歲的時候
Whether the parents are divorced or separated
父母是否離婚或分居
Because I just used twelve
因為剛剛用的都是十二
then thirteen to sixteen
然後十三到十六
Then I'll see if you're fifteen to cut the root
那我看看你十五歲來切根
what's the difference
會有什麼不一樣
This is an academic research to try
這就做學術研究要嘗試嘛
Then this is all there
然後這個都是有
we all do it
我們都有這樣做
I just take this example
我只要舉這個例
Let's see marriage first
我們先看出婚
You will see the marriage rate in Yilan
你會看到宜蘭的出婚率
taller than them
比他們高
less educated parents
父母教育程度較低的
more likely to find marriage
比較可能會找婚
But in terms of family income
可是家庭收入來看
Male household income and financial status
男性家庭收入財務狀況
more abundant
越充裕的
He is more likely to marry
他出婚可能性越高
no effect on women
對女性沒有影響
look at this get out of prison
你看看這個出獄
It seems to be the same as the complete copy
好像是完全的Copy都一樣
But here women come out
可是在這裡女性出來了
didn't it matter just now?
剛剛不重要嘛
The female family gave back
女性家庭還給了
less abundant more likely
比較不充裕的比較可能
Giving birth, this place is different
生孩子,就這個地方有不一樣
Let's use this method to explain one by one
我們就用這個辦法一個一個的去解釋
You look like first marriage too
你看像初婚也一樣
Men with good family relationships will marry early
家庭關係好的人男性會早婚
no effect on women
對女性沒影響
However, when the age of 15, the parents were divorced or separated.
可是15歲的時候父母已經離婚或分居的
It has no effect on men, but on women it will lead to early marriage
對男性沒有影響,對女性反而會早婚
clear gender difference
很明顯的性別差異
I am consistent with many documents
自己跟很多文獻都是相合的
Early Childhood is the same
早育也一樣
You see, if the family relationship is good, men will give birth early
你看家庭關係好,男性會早育
Parents divorce, women will have early childbearing
父母離婚,女性會早育
no effect on other
對其他沒有影響
we sit all the way
我們這樣一路坐下去
Conclusions are structural, relational and normative factors
結論就是結構性、關係性、規範性因素
will affect the marriage and childbearing of Taiwan's younger generation
都會影響台灣年輕世代的婚姻和生育
For researchers
對研究人員來講
Some important disguises you will come into contact with when studying architecture
你研究架構所要接觸的一些重要變相
Such a result
出了這樣的成果
psychologically happy
心理就開心不已
then on the other hand
然後另外一方面
Importantly, the effect of gender differences
很重要是性別差異的效果
very obvious
非常的明顯
for men
對男性來講
His family income was relatively high before he was a teenager
他青少年前家庭收入比較高
good family relationship
家人之間關係好
And he currently has a job
而且他目前有工作的
He is more likely to marry and have children before the age of 28
他比較可能在28歲前又結婚又生育
But for women
可是對女性來講
If parents are divorced or separated
如果父母已經離婚或分居的
He is more likely to marry and have children
他比較可能又結婚又生育
But when he was a teenager, his family income was high
可是青少年期他家庭收入高
he currently has a job
他自己目前有工作的
he is less likely to marry
他比較不可能結婚
less likely to have children
也比較不可能生育
So this is the model that is equal to the income of the western economy
所以這個就是等於西方經濟收入的那個模式
Get verified here
在這裡就得到驗證
so in short
所以簡單來講
Have financial ability and early positive family life experience
有經濟能力跟早期正面家庭生活經驗
Powerful masculinity is negative for women
有力男性可是對女性是負面的
And if the parents divorce before the middle teens,
而父母在青少年中期之前就離婚的話
More likely to cause women's early marriage and early childbearing
比較可能造成女性的早婚和早育
That is, he may come from an environment that is less resource-advantaged
也就是他可能是來自比較資源不利的環境
he needs a relationship
他需要一個relationship
What about the next 31 years old?
那接下來31歲情況又是如何
Every researcher has their own unique
每一個研究人員有自己不太一樣的
research interest and the point of view he wants to explore
研究興趣跟他想要探討的觀點
So many interviewees said why they always have the same problem
所以很多那個受訪者說為什麼老是為一樣的問題
Because every stage is different
因為每個階段都不一樣嘛
The overall look will be different, right?
整體看起來就會不一樣呀 對不對
so let's look at this
所以我們來看看這個
What Professor Liu Jiahua of Tamkang said about our previous Post
淡江劉家華教授說的我們以前的Post
He made some long-term effects on the integrity of the family structure
他就做了一些家庭結構完整性的長期影響
You want to see if there is a difference for gender
你想看看對性別是不是會產生差異
OK, let's combine the two sets of samples.
好 我們把兩組樣本都合起來來看
The one just now was shown to you with a national art sample
剛剛那個是用國藝樣本給你們看
Both groups look together
這兩組都合起來看
You can see that about 76.4 means that the parents are still there
你可以看得到大概76.4是雙親還在
No divorce, one parent is dead
沒有離婚 那有一位父母已經過世人
Already 14% at an average age of 61
已經有14% 就是在平均61歲的時候
Then the divorce rate is about 9.7, which is about 10%.
然後離婚大概是9.7 就是10%左右
Then the marital status of the parents
那麼父母婚姻狀態
You said the two-parent marriage continued and the parents were divorced.
你說雙親婚姻持續 父母已經離婚
Percentage of married to one of the deceased parents
父母之一過世 跟他結婚的百分比
That's probably how marriage lasts up to
大概是這樣 婚姻持續的最高
But the parents are divorced
可是父母已經離婚
we break it down into so many stages
我們就把它分成這麼多階段
one is a baby wife
一個是幼兒妻
A primary school period, a teenage period, a college period, and an adult period
一個國小期,一個是青少年期,一個大學期,一個成人期
As you can see, ages 6 to 17 are significantly lower, very much
你可以看得到,6到17歲非常明顯的低,非常多
Because the average parental divorce is 36, but only 31 in these two stages
因為父母離婚平均是36,可是在這兩個階段只有31
However, children whose parents divorced in childhood were most likely to marry
可是,父母如果在兒童期就離婚的孩子,最可能結婚
It depends on whether there is any difference between men and women. These three are the ones I explained just now.
那看男女有沒有差別,這三個就是剛剛我解釋過的
Since we are 6 to 12 and 13 to 17 are low, we have to combine them
我們既然6到12,13到17很低,我們就要合併起來
You can see that among those whose parents are divorced, it affects men the most
你可以看得到,父母已經離婚的人當中對男性影響最大
If he has no parents in childhood, he is most likely to marry early, and he will marry like this
如果他幼兒期就沒有父母,他最可能早婚,就結婚了就這樣子講
It cannot be said that he married early, because he is 31 years old, but when he is at school age, he is the least likely to get married
不能說早婚,因為有31歲,可是在他就學齡的時候,最不可能結婚
The same is true for women. After a woman reaches adulthood, her parents will divorce and she will rise again.
女的也一樣,女的到成人後,父母離婚他又會上升
Some people say that it may be better to use a picture to represent this thing
那這個東西有人說,可能用圖來表示會比較好
more obvious isn't it
比較明顯是嗎
For me I think the number is more obvious
對我來說我覺得數目比較明顯
but it's okay you see
不過沒關係 你看
When children are six to seven years old
小孩子在六到七七歲的時候
It's really unlikely to get married.
的確是比較不可能結婚的
This gray one is all
這個灰色的是全體
blue is male
藍色是男的
red is rain
紅色是雨的
Just look at the time from one to fifteen years old
就你看一到十五歲的時候
Boys are the most likely to marry, right?
男生是最可能結婚 對不對
That woman's parents divorced during adulthood
那女性在成年期父母離婚
He is also more likely to marry
他也比較可能結婚
Then come down again, what do you think?
那再下來 你怎麼看
you first than
你先比
Is that a category just now?
那剛剛那個是一個類別嘛
did not look together
沒有合起來看
you can't just say for sure
你不能就只確定說
It's really bad to get a divorce.
那真的離婚就很不好
worse than dead parents
比父母死亡還不好
you don't know
你並不知道
because you watch it together
因為你們一起放在一起看
if you look at it together
如果你放在一起看
you will find
你會發現
One of the parents died is the least likely to marry
父母之一過世是最不可能結婚
He's more prominent than a divorce
他的顯著度比離婚還要多
So let's confirm this first
所以我們先把這個確認了
see you later
那接下來再看
what about divorce
那麼離婚呢
I still divide these time points the same
我還是一樣分這幾個時間點
Compared with the death of one of the parents
跟父母之一過世去比
discovering that one of the parents has passed away
發現父母之一過世
is a persistent and significant
是一持續的顯著
at least for men
至少對男性是這樣
And at school age
而且在學齡的時候
if parents divorce
如果父母離婚的話
Significantly lower for men too
對男性也是顯著的低
Not so serious for women
對女性倒沒有那麼嚴重
Is that clear?
這樣很清楚了吧
Then next this
然後接下來這個
tell us what
告訴我們什麼
At least we are 31 years old
至少我們對31歲
Adult children come to see
成年子女來看
you and family structure
你跟家庭結構
completely complete compared to
完全完整相比之下
The death of a parent will reduce the
父母過世會降低
possibility of marriage
結婚的可能性
but the parents divorced
但是父母離婚
did not achieve a significant effect
並沒有達到顯著效果
it looks like you just
這樣看起來好像你剛剛
Is the divorce you want to talk about gone?
想要講的離婚都不見了嗎
But this place is here
可是這個地方在啊
so we see
所以我們就看到
sooner or later parents divorce
父母離婚的早晚
Impact on children's likelihood of marriage
對子女結婚可能性的影響
son is Mr.
兒子是先生後將
The daughter was born first
女兒是先降後生
right
對不對
right, right?
對啊 對不對
son is Mr.
兒子是先生後將
The daughter was born first
女兒是先降後生
The third
第三個
The point of divorce between parents is children
父母離婚點在子女
The greatest impact on men
對於男性有影響最大
more dangerous for men
對於男性更危險
Okay, so just at this point we saw that one of the parents passed away.
好 那麼剛剛這一點給大家看到父母之一過世
The same is true for men
對男性也是一樣有很大的
obvious impact
就很明顯的衝擊
So whether it's divorce or death
所以不管是離婚或過世
The family structure has changed
家庭結構都改變了
The marriage of the sons as adults
這對兒子成年後的結婚
have a negative impact
產生負面的影響
So it's probably like this
所以大概是這樣
ok so to put it simply
好 那所以簡單來講
I just spent a little more time talking to you about the above
把剛剛上面我花了多一點時間跟大家講
Structural Relational Factors Long-Term Effects
結構性 關係性 因素 長期影響
Just take this early family experience of parental divorce
單單以經歷父母離婚的這種早期家庭經驗來說
The conclusions of our current research can be condensed into these few sentences
我們目前研究的結論大概就可以濃縮成這幾句
You can see the divorce of childhood parents
大家可以看到兒童期父母離婚
You're More Likely To Date You're Pregnant Before Marriage
你比較可能會約會你婚前懷孕
but not early marriage
可是不是早婚
But if the teenage parents divorce
可是如果親少年期父母離婚的話
you don't want to get married
你比較不想結婚
but for women
可是對女的來說
Instead, it increases his chances of early marriage and early childbearing
反而提高他早婚與早育的機率
Parent-child conflict in the family relationship
那家庭關係方面親子衝突
Often take care of the children and leave the family to get married
往往照顧孩子就離開家庭去結婚
but see
可是看到
parental conflict not parent-child conflict
父母衝突 不是親子衝突的
He doesn't want to get married
他反而不想結婚
He is also less likely to marry early
他也比較不會早婚
That family cohesion is high
那家庭凝聚力高
Family relationship plays a role in boys' early marriage and early childbearing
家庭關係對男生的早婚早育有吹聲效果
So this is also an example
所以這也是一個例主點
Said that the government wants people to get married and have children all the time
說政府一天到晚要人家這個結婚生孩子的話
In fact, what should be tried is
其實應該要努力的是
work hard on family education
要在家庭教育上努力
At least for men it is very noticeable effect
至少對男性是很有明顯的效果
OK, then I'll move on to the second topic.
好 那我就進入第二個題目
It is our educational diversion
就是我們的教育分流
Then this educational diversion
那麼這個教育分流
our many studies
我們許許多多的研究
I'm doing a little integration here
我在這裡稍微做個整合
The first diversion was probably when we were in high school
第一次分流大概是我們在高中的時候
18 years old for the second diversion
第二次分流就18歲
Then when the first average
那麼第一次平均的時候
you can see about half and half
你可以看得到大概一半一半
It is about half and half for those who study high value or junior college in high school
念高中念高值或專科大概是一半一半
at the age of 18
到了18歲的時候
You can see that 74% of high school students went to colleges and universities
你可以看得到高中去生大專院校的有74%
But there are also 10% who take the exam
可是也有10%去考課大
then in
那麼在
When I was a freshman and when I was a senior in high school, 14 was still there
大一的時候 高三的時候 有14還在
I've already gone to work or to tutoring
就已經去工作 或者去補習了
As for the 50% of this
至於那個50%的這個
What about the Higher Vocational Technology University, you can see it
高職生科技大學的呢 你可以看得到
4.7% went to university
升大學的有4.7%
Most are still in HKUST
大多數還是在科大
But the rate of work is of course very high
可是工作的比率當然就非常高
It is also conceivable
這也是可以想見的
Taiwan's education competition, this is
台灣教育的競爭 這個就
I guess none of us would
我想我們大家大概都不會
I won't doubt it, so I can skip it here
不會懷疑 所以這裡面就可以跳開
In particular, I think we've seen in research
尤其我覺得我們在研究中看到
Families and schools actually affect children's academic performance
家庭跟學校其實對孩子的學業表現
is very consistent
是非常一致的
i most remember i used to say
我最記得我常常講
Because Professor Zhou Yuhui and Professor Huang Langman
因為周育慧教授跟黃朗文教授
Our colleagues have done
我們這些同仁曾經做過
Quality of life of middle-aged parents
中年父母的生活品質
Of course parent-child relationship is very important
那當然親子關係是非常重要的
a factor but
一個因素 可是
I don't think the West will have this thing
這個東西我想西方不會有
Children's homework is good for mother's this
小孩子功課好對母親的這個
Living Responsible Significant Role
生活負責 顯著的作用
think about how interesting it is
你想想看這多有意思
Is this already mentioned?
這是不是就已經講到
We talked about a lot of things in context
我們講到這一大堆的東西就是在脈絡下
right
對不對
good
好
So we started to focus on the research topic of educational diversion
所以我們一開始針對教育分流的研究課題
Let's say from the perspective of mental health trajectory
我們說從心理健康軌跡來看
We just have a set of topics
我們剛好有一組題目
we use it every time
我們就每次都用它
This group of questions is probably the only question
這一組題目大概是唯一一個問句
guys i know some of you say
各位我知道你們有些人說
when we visit
我們去訪問的時候
Because he has answered it ten times
因為他已經答了十來遍了
so visit him
所以訪問問他
do you have this or something
你有沒有這個什麼
none below none
沒有下面都沒有
then turn the page
那就翻頁
Because he has answered more than ten times
因為他已經答十多遍
He didn't even have that page
他照那一頁他都沒有
just turn the page
翻頁就翻過去
don't suddenly grow old sometimes
不要突然有時候年紀長大
still will be different
還是會不一樣的
still have to ask
還是要問一下
good
好
Then our sample ranges from the first wave to the twenty-seventh year old
那我們樣本大概從第一波到第二十七歲
I can show you
可以給大家看
what about the other
那另外呢
Professor Fan Ganghua and I have worked together
在做范剛華教授跟我曾經合作過
We take high school or above
我們就取高中職以上
see how it's been for a while
看這一段時間到底是怎麼樣
Students who do not study because they graduated from junior high school
因為國中畢業就不念書的學生
Also the sample of departures is not that high
還有離開的樣本並不是那麼高
This is for everyone to see
這是給大家看
This is the most typical
這是最典型
In the growth process of Chinese and American teenagers
中美的青少年成長歷程中
his melancholic state
他憂鬱整壯的情況
you can see
你可以看得到
He started skyrocketing to 18 when he was 15
他在15歲的時候開始飆升到18歲
very high
很高
The red ones are women and the blue ones are men
紅的都是女的 藍的都是男的
black is average
黑的就是平均
But from here, it began to slowly plateau
可是到這裡就開始慢慢走向高原期
This is what we call
這是一個我們把它叫做
physiological maturation model
生理成熟模式
this is a natural
這就是一個自然
Naturally it should look like this
自然應該是長這個樣子的
So what is Taiwan like?
所以我們台灣是怎麼樣呢
is so
是這樣
Last time I told you a little bit about this
我們這個上一次我有稍微跟大家講到
22 years old
22歲
15 years old with the highest depression
15歲憂鬱最高
Why are you going to high school?
為什麼要考高中了
16 years old so happy
16歲好高興
17 years old
17歲不行了
At the age of 18, I started to be tall again, right?
18歲又開始高了 有沒有
going to university
要考大學
we were weird
我們那時候很奇怪
I don't know why 20 is so tall
不知道為什麼20歲這麼高
Later we were thinking
後來我們在想
Some of the 20-year-olds have graduated from higher vocational schools
20歲當中有一些是已經高職畢業
Served in the military for two years
已經兩年制的當兵
he has his certain pressure
他有他一定的壓力
Back then we only saw here
當年我們只看到這裡
then slowly descend
然後接下來慢慢下降
Is that so until 27
是不是這樣 一直到27
In fact, it should add 31
其實應該加31
Just need to continue to add 31
剛好還要繼續加31
then you can watch girls
然後你可以看女生
Girls are taller than boys all over the world
全世界都是女生比男生高
But here there is a
可是在這裡有一個
When I graduated from university at the age of 22
22歲大學畢業的時候
is there a merge point
是有一個合併點
What about the boys?
那男生呢 你看
Boys will be happier all the way
男生一路都會比較開心
But here he is taller
可是到這個地方他也高起來了
22 years old when everyone graduated
22歲大家都畢業的時候
a little nervous scary
有點緊張 可怕
I went down again and felt good again
又下去了 又覺得自己不錯
Boys only feel good about themselves
男生只有自己覺得不錯的
I feel good about this quality
這個品質我覺得滿好的
we will see later
在後面我們都會看到
I will push and add a fun one for you to see
我都會推遞加一個好玩的給你們看
remind me
要提醒我
Next, let's talk about the teacher
接下來我們放剛話老師
that means let's go and see
就是說我們去看
Educate your diversion about a person
教育你的分流對一個人
What is the effect
到底有什麼影響
You see it's like a high school
你看到這是高職一樣
15 18 22
15 18 22
This is a vocational college graduate
這是高職 高職畢業生而已
they are practicing
他們有在練書
This group has always had the highest
這一組一直是有最高的
Has grown up
有育成狀
Then this is high school
那這個就高中
He only went to high school and didn't continue
他只念到高中就沒有繼續念
You see he seems to be happy
你看他就好像還開心
But at 22 he's a little nervous
可是到了22歲他有點緊張
Graduating from high school is somewhat different from graduating from higher vocational education in the job market
高中畢業跟高職畢業在求職市場上多少有一點不同
Because your training human capital is not the same
因為你有的訓練人力資本是不太一樣的
University of Science and Technology
科技大學
Technological universities are arguably doing well
科技大學可以說是表現得很好
He's a little lower, a little lower all the way
他比較低一點 一路都低一點
what about university
大學呢
He's here, if you're a senior
他在 如果你高職不算
He was tallest when he was 15
他在15歲的時候最高
At the age of 18 is also the highest
在18歲也最高
At the age of 20, it is still quite tall, like high school
到20歲還是相當的高跟高中一樣
But after you turned 24, did you notice him?
可是到了24歲以後你有沒有注意到他
rapid descent
急速的下降
Of course they have a commergence
當然他們有一個commergence
But at least he is the most descended
可是至少他還是最下降的
Then let's say, let's see if there is any difference in the region
那我們就說 那我們看看地區有沒有不一樣
Red is Taipei Line
紅色的是台北線
Is it a bit like a high school?
有沒有一點像高職了
that feeling
那個那個感覺
That Taipei City is this blue
那台北市就是這個藍色的
At first it seemed that Yilan was the happiest
開始好像宜蘭都是最高興的
Just a little nervous at 20
就在20歲的時候稍微緊張一點
to be honest
坦白講
when i was getting ready i really felt
我在準備的時候我真的覺得
In 20 years, I really don't know more than I know
20年來我不知道的實在比知道的多
There are always questions coming out, I really don't know
一直有題目出來我真的不知道
what's up with this 20 year old
這個20歲是怎麼回事
i still don't know
我就還是不知道
so really sorry
所以真的很抱歉
I hope that someone will continue to study in the future
希望後期有人大家繼續去研究
But you see that Yilan is really
可是你看到宜蘭真的就是
quality of life will be better
生活品質會好一點
So this thing makes us think
所以這個東西就讓我們想
Could it have something to do with the structure of his family?
會不會跟他的家庭的結構有關係
family's structural capital
就是家庭的結構性資本
As far as we found out, this blue one is
就我們發現這個藍色的是
Dad has a college degree or above
爸爸有專科以上學歷的
Good shape
優裕整狀
dad didn't
爸爸沒有的
You see, dad doesn't actually have
你看爸爸沒有的其實
always lower, right?
一直比較低一點對不對
Especially in the 1920's it was obvious
尤其在1920歲的時候很明顯
But at the age of 22
可是到了22歲的時候
The effect of the family's resources appears
家庭的資源的效果就出現了
when you apply for a job
當你要求職的時候
You will find that you have a father who is more educated
你會發現你有一個教育程度比較高的父親
he can discuss with you
他可以跟你討論
I can tell you some things
可以跟你介紹的一些情況
It's different from nothing
跟沒有的是不一樣的
What about family relations?
家庭關係呢
The blue one is a good family relationship
這個藍色的是家庭關係好
The red color means that the family relationship is relatively bad.
那紅色是家庭關係比較不好
As long as it is a bad relationship, it goes all the way and gets bigger and bigger.
那只要是不好的關係是一路而且延伸越來越大
It's because this study made me think of saying
就是因為這個研究讓我想到說
Although Yuyu's overall status and the two entrance exams correspond to each other
雖然優裕整狀跟兩次聯考相互應
There is an obvious educational diversion effect
有明顯教育分流效果
But the family vein has its double effect
但是家庭脈絡有它的雙級效果
Appears in middle school and early adulthood
國中跟成年初期都會出現
and as it stands
而且就目前看來
like family relationship
好像家庭關係
more pronounced than family structure
比家庭結構效果還要明顯
We are here if you are interested in this
我們在座如果大家對這個有興趣的
welcome a lot of research
歡迎多多研究
Because these materials have been released
因為這些資料都已經釋出了
Anyone can go online to do academic research
誰都可以上網去去做學術研究
The growth trajectory of the school is obvious
那學校脈絡很明顯的成長軌跡
has a long-term effect on
有個長期的效果在
ok so here we go
好所以做到這裡呢
I'll go on to say that sociologists care more about the underprivileged
我接下來就說社會學家比較關心弱勢群體
among our vulnerable
在我們的弱勢群體中
We have a set of questions that if you are interviewed here
我們有一組題目如果在座受訪的
This is all about deviant behavior
這都是為有關偏差行為
So I ask the current Taipei University
所以呢我就拜託現在的台北大學
Head of Department of Social Studies Chen Yifu
社會學習系主任陳奕福
He was our first generation research assistant
他是我們第一代的研究助理
So he went for three weeks
所以他就去三個禮拜
all week all weekend
整個禮拜整個週末
Just keep writing back and forth with me
就跟我不斷的書信往返
So this result is hot
所以這個結果是熱呼呼的
Everyone can take a look
大家可以看一下
we care about the disadvantaged
我們關心若是群體
We also want to see from this
我們也想要由此來看到
What is the multi-development model?
多元發展模式是怎麼一回事
Then if you say deviant behavior
然後你如果說偏差行為
is a body indicator
是個身體的指標
so-called depressive symptoms
那麼所謂憂鬱症狀
It's a psychological indicator
就是心理的指標
Is there any correlation between these two indicators?
這兩個指標間有沒有什麼相關
Here's what we all want to know
這是我們每個人都會想要知道的情況
right
對不對
someone nodded
有人點頭
Come on, let's take a look
來 大家看一下
Indicators of our biased behavior
我們偏差行為指標
Probably these ten
大概就是這十個
result
結果
Melancholy, he used it from the age of 13 to the age of 18
憂鬱他就從他13歲用到18歲
It was found that four groups can be distinguished
發現可以分出四組
come everybody
來 各位
this
這個
This is called the highest
這個是叫做最高的
About 9.2% of him are tall all the way
他大概有9.2%的人是一路都很高
lowest here
最低的在這
The lowest is of course the most
最低的當然最多啦
he is always the lowest
他永遠是最低
Turns out jumping a little bit at 15 when it was stressful
結果在15歲壓力大的時候稍微跳一下
less obvious jump
跳得不太明顯
Another group of people in the literature
另外有一組人在文獻上
The literature will also tell you
文獻上也會跟你說
He's going to have a flare-up in his mid-teens
他在青少年中期會突發一下
so parents don't be nervous
所以父母不要緊張
22% of this group of people
這一批人22%
In his 15-year-old burst he fell again
他在15歲的突發他又掉下來了
So this group of people is normal
所以這一批人是正常的
Taiwan is different from Europe and the United States
台灣跟歐美不一樣的地方
That is to recall what I just said
也就是回憶我剛講
A whole bunch of us showing up another set
一大堆的是我們出現另外一組
Blue will rise to the group at the age of 15 and 18
藍色在15歲 18歲都會上升組
I think this is really
我覺得這個真的就是
Related to our educational diversion
跟我們教育分流有關
He is always there
他就是永遠處在那個
under pressure
聯考的壓力下
Some say he is 30 years old
有人說他到30歲
I dreamed that he was taking an exam
做夢還夢見他在考試
so many years
那麼多年
so you can see
所以你可以看得到
This is with Mofit
這跟Mofit
His theory of deviant development is the same
他的偏差發展理論是一樣
It's just that we have one more in Taiwan
只是我們台灣多了這麼一個
Deviation
偏差的情況
so i want to say
所以我就想說
Then I see these four groups of people
那我看這四組人
how about his depression
他憂鬱情緒怎麼樣呢
Of course this thing is all the way up
當然這個東西一路高的人
he is depressed
他是憂鬱的
But in the end, there is not much difference
可是到後面其實就差別不大了
did you notice
你有沒有注意到
That group is what I'm talking about
那這一批就是我講的
Nervous when the face is good
臉好的時候很緊張
This green is only once
這個綠色就是只有一次
This is relatively low
這個是比較低的
no matter who you are at 15
不管你是誰在15歲
all very nervous
統統很緊張
So the pressure of our high school entrance examination
所以我們考高中的壓力
We also talked about it last time
我們上回也講過
It is much more stressful than going to college
就本來就是比考大學壓力要大得多
So this is his 19 to 30 years old
那麼這個就是他19歲到30歲
You can see a little bump here
你可以看到這邊有一點bump
But then converge again
可是後面又converge
little difference
就差別不大
So overall
所以整體來看
You can see this line is very obvious
你看這個線條就很明顯了
We follow this wave all the way
我們這一波一路一路跟
It's their link
就是他們的連記這樣
follow all the way
一路一路跟
You can see this time low down
你可以看到這個時候低下來
go up again
又上去
this time at the age of 20
這個時候在20歲的時候
This is the group I'm talking about
就是這一批就是我講的
Our special groups in Taiwan
我們臺灣特殊群體
He was very tall when he was 20 years old
就20歲的時候都特別的高
then to the back
然後到後面
Everyone is connected again
又大家又連接下來了
so i'm interested
所以我就很有興趣
I said okay don't let me take a look
我說可以不要讓我看一看
these four groups of people
這四組人
After we control all the disguises
我們控制所有的變相之後
Is this disguise still obvious?
這一個變相是不是還是顯著
Then I present these salient
那我就呈現這些顯著
show you please watch this
給你看 請你看這個
It is the 9.2% just mentioned
就是剛剛講的9.2%
The group with the highest deviant behavior all the way
那個一路都是最高的偏差行為的那一組
Indeed, there are many boys
的確 男生多
He is likely to come from a single-parent family
他是來自單親家庭可能性高
His highest education is lower than others, right?
他最高學歷比人家都低 對不對
Very high frequency of smoking
抽菸頻率特別高
GPC we ask you how many packs you smoke a day, etc.
GPC我們問你一天抽幾包 等等等等
The question is very detailed, just to do some research
問得很細 就是為了要做一些研究
And the frequency of drinking is also higher than others
然後喝酒的頻率也比人家高
But is he the same as that
可是他是不是跟那個一樣
his traditional gender role he is extra tall
他傳統的性別角色他特別高
It's more conservative. He will be more conservative.
就是比較保守 他會比較保守
He is conservative in many views
對很多看法他是比較保守
Although he has a high level of deviant behavior
他雖然自己偏差行為很高
In fact, his attitude is relatively conservative.
其實他的態度上是比較保守的
do you feel depressed
你會覺得壓抑嗎
Actually not working class
其實不會 勞工階級
Also more conservative than white-collar workers
也比白領階級更為保守
This is certain at this time
這是一定的 這時候
All countries in the world are like this
這世界各國都這樣
Okay, next family drama
好 接下來家庭凌劇力
He was so low back then that's why he had all sorts of deviant behavior
他那個時候這麼低 所以他才有各種偏差行為
Performance
的表現
Friends support, probably no one particularly likes this kind of person
朋友支持大概不會有人特別喜歡這種人
So he is also very low
所以他也特別低
Married or not, of course not as good as this group
有沒有結婚 當然不如這一組
But I was very depressed and found that this is a very significant high
可是我非常壓抑發現 這個是非常顯著的高
He's most likely to start a business when he's 31
他最可能會創業 在他31歲的時候
And he earns more than all of them
而且他的收入比他們都高
I'm relieved after we finally got this result the night before...
我們終於在大前天晚上得到這個結果以後我就安心了
Otherwise, I don't know how to tell you
要不然我不知道怎麼跟各位講
So I'm going to tell you that after the high deviance group enters adulthood,
所以我要告訴各位 高偏差群邁入成年期之後
On the contrary, his entrepreneurship and his income are the highest
反而他的創業跟他的收入是最高的
So you need to know this
所以這個東西你就要知道
He's because of his high biased orientation
他就是因為他有高偏差的這個取向
So his explosive power will be different
所以他的那個爆發力也會比較不一樣
So we are doing a very preliminary analysis of this thing now.
所以這個東西我們現在是做很初步分析
control a bunch of necessary disguises
控制一堆必要的變相
It is also possible to obtain such remarkable results
還可以得到這麼顯著的結果
we have to prove it for him
我們要替他證明
So next, some of our colleagues will do adult education and employment
那所以接下來我們有一些同仁就做成年期的教育就業
School to Work Transition
學校到工作的轉型
This seems to be a very popular topic in the world
這個像是全世界非常紅的一個題目
Then our diversion is very similar to Germany
那麼我們的分流跟德國很相近
But it's not the same
可是又不太一樣
When we were 15 years old, were we divided into high school and high school?
我們15歲的時候就分高中高職嘛
then divide later
然後後來再分
that's for us
那可是對我們來說
We also have some special localization considerations
我們還有一些特別在地化的考量
then we also want to know
那我們也想知道
How is educational achievement related generationally
教育成就的代先關聯如何
School qualifications, occupations, etc.
學校學歷職業等等的條件
so what
所以呢
ok please take a look
好 請大家看一下
At the age of 31, our batch of samples
31歲的時候我們這一批樣本
The actual degree is like this
實際學歷是這樣的
most are college graduates
大多數人是大學畢業
Graduated from a junior college Graduated from a vocational school
專科畢業 高職畢業
Master's degree is very high
碩士畢業非常的高
Because now it's like a master's class
因為現在好像碩士班
More open to young people to read
比較開放給年輕人去讀
we just say to us today
我們就今天向我們就說
take a look
看一下好不好
when he was 15 or 18
他15歲 18歲的時候
we all asked a question
我們都問過一個問題
How high of a degree do you hope you can study in the future?
你希望你將來可以念到多高的學歷
ok you can see
好 你可以看得到
When I graduated from junior high school at the age of 15
15歲國中畢業的時候
Many people say that I will study until I graduate from a vocational school
很多人說我要念到高職畢業
Do you have
有沒有
But when he was 18, he stopped talking like that.
可到18歲他就沒有這樣講了
But at the age of 31
可是到31歲的時候
The real degree is slightly higher
真正學歷反而稍微高一點
Because maybe he missed
因為可能他本來是很想念
master's degree
大學念碩士的
However, some subjective and objective conditions may not be able to match
可是有些主客觀條件未必能夠配合
so he moved up a little bit
所以他稍微升了一點
so let's see
所以就讓大家看一下
Therefore, the educator expects educational achievements similar to his own
所以教育期望跟他自己習近的教育成就
We still have parents' educational expectations
我們還有父母的教育期望
There are also teacher's educational expectations
也有老師的教育期望
Teachers and parents are quite converged
老師跟家長是相當converged
We also remember the children in Yilan
我們也記得好像宜蘭的小孩子
When I was in Guoyi, I was very happy that the volume chain was very high
在國藝的時候是都很高興量鏈很高
When he was in third grade, he would return to a comparison
到國三他就回到一個比較
some practical expectations
務實面的一些期望
so to speak
可以這樣講
good
好
what's next
那接下來呢
Let's ask Professor Liu to take a look
我們就請劉將來教授看看
What is the background profile of this sample?
這個樣本的背景概況到底是怎麼樣
About 38% are married
大概有38%已婚
23% have given birth
23%已經生育
i am surprised
我很訝異
32-year-olds think they are in normal health
32歲的人竟然都覺得自己健康狀況普通
I don't know why
那不曉得為什麼
i thought i should be happy
我以為應該很高采對
may be really ordinary
可能是真的普通
That
那
Then the father's family background
然後父親的家庭背景
Father's college degree or above is 24
父親大專以上的是24
Compared with the 70s we see now
跟我們現在看到的70幾
It's a big difference
來比的話差很大
so here
所以這裡
This upward mobility in education is very evident
教育的這個向上流動是非常明顯的
Then their income on average is like this
然後他們的收入在平均是這樣
there are people in management
那有做管理階層的人
probably the same
大概也是這樣
So
那麼
The average number of years of schooling is 15.7
在平均教育年數是15.7
That
那
come and see this
來看這個好了
this is faster
這比較快
About 70% of people are employed
大概70%人是有工作
But you need to know that the average company size is 3.5
可是你要知道平均的公司規模是3.5
so really small business
所以是真的小企業
Most of them are working in small companies.
大概都是在很小的公司在工作
Not the TSMC you think of
不是你想到的台積電
absolutely not
絕對不是
probably so
大概是這樣
good
好
so what
所以呢
By gender you can see
依性別來分你看得到
If we divide it into four categories
我們如果把它分成四類
This top national
這個頂尖國立
It is the classification of the ten schools listed by the Ministry of Education
就是到教育部的那十個學校的分類
Because I said that Taiwan is more interested in this
因為我就說這個是我們台灣比較有興趣
Knowing that their final education is connected with his employment one by one
知道他們最後教育跟他就業的一個一個一個連結
You see it is probably like this below the junior college level
你看到大專以下大概是這樣
males are higher than females
男性高於女性
most at private colleges
大多數人在私立大學
This is no problem, probably everyone agrees
這個是沒有問題大概都會同意
The average national university here is a little less than the top university
那一般國立大學在這裡頂尖大學是少一點
If the achievement of Fujing education
如果以復經教育成就
The revival itself is below the specialist level
復興本身在專科以下的
This child is more likely to have only a junior college or below
這個子女比較可能也只有專科以下
or a private university
或者是私立大學
But if Fuxing has a college degree or above
可是復興若是專科以上的
he is in national university
他在國立大學
You can see that compared to him, he will be obviously taller.
你看這樣相比他就會很明顯的會比較高
So that's what we're talking about with shoulder flow
所以這也就是我們講的這個帶肩流動的問題
This is the most basic one-by-one association
這是最最基本的一個一個一個關聯
mother too
母親也一樣
Then if you divide it again, you can see
那如果再分呢你看得到
Taipei is a national university and top universities
台北是念國立大學跟頂尖大學的
It is higher than Taipei and Yilan
比台北卸宜蘭都要高
Taipei Line and Yilan can only be read in the language of colleges and universities
台北線跟宜蘭唸只有大專語下
The proportion of those who did not study college is higher than that of Taipei City
沒有唸大專的比例比台北市高
Regional differences exist
地區性差異它就是存在
The distribution of educational resources is not the same
教育資源分配是不太一樣
So in the end we agreed
所以最後我們說好
Then let's see how your school and your labor market are doing.
那我們看看你學校跟你勞動市場結果怎麼樣
We take private universities
我們拿私立大學就是
More than half of the people are studying in private universities as a reference group
一半以上人都唸私立大學做參考組
Compared with him, those who did not go to university in college language
大專語下沒唸大學的跟他比
Compared with him, those who study in National University
唸國立大學的跟他比
Those who go to top universities can compare with him
唸頂尖大學的跟他比
Then empty out a lot of stuff
然後空去一大堆東西之後
Discover Top National Universities for People
發現頂尖國立大學的人
It is more likely that the monthly salary is higher than that of private universities
比較可能每月薪資比私立大學的高
Gao Gao, this is the proof
高高這個就是就是證嘛
then this is about
那麼這個是講
National universities can have about 4% more
國立大學大概是可以有多百分之四
And top universities can even reach
而頂尖大學甚至可以達到
Twenty-two percent is 2 percent better than private universities
二十二百分之二就是比私立大學
It's the same with the salary and the management class is interesting
這也一樣工資也一樣管理階層就很有意思
you'll find out you don't go to college
你會發現你不唸大學的
and only national university students
和只有唸國立大學的
with private university
跟私立大學
less likely to be a manager
反而比較不可能當管理者
Do you understand me?
這樣聽懂我意思嗎
If you are studying at a private university
如果你是念私立大學的
you don't go to college
你比不念大學的
And those who study in general state universities
以及念一般國立大學的
More opportunities to be a manager
更有機會去當管理的人
But if the job is satisfactory
可是工作滿意來看的話
Compared with private universities
這個跟私立大學比
this person is satisfied
這個人很滿意
he didn't go to college
他沒有念大學
he's having fun too
他做得也很開心
But with that national university
可是跟那個國立大學
For top thousand universities
頂千大學來講
Everyone is more satisfied than him
大家都比他滿意
What does this mean
這什麼意思
family forced better
家庭被迫比較好
Higher chances of entering national universities
進入國立大學機會比較高
this is what we've all been
這是我們都已經
Repeated lectures on various educational research
各種教育研究的一再講
And the salary after graduating from national university
而國立大學畢業後的薪資
is relatively high
是比較高的
Do you have
有沒有
This is not a problem
這是沒有問題的
so high tuition
所以高學費
this subsidy policy
這個貼補政策
Maybe it's really poor people who make up for it
可能是真的窮人去補
rich man
有錢人
This is indeed a concern
這的確是有這個顧慮
the other one
那另外一個
This is a person from a private university
這個就私立大學的人
percentage of his managerial positions
他擔任管理職的比例
is relatively high
是比較高的
But he's not in a management position in a big company
可是他不是在大公司擔任管理職
So his salary is not high or low
所以他薪資並不高比較低
and lower job satisfaction
而且工作滿意度也比較低
so you know what I mean, right?
這樣你們就懂我的意思了嘛 對不對
Then come and see
那這樣子的話你來看
His management experience will affect his future promotion
他管理經驗對他未來升遷
Competing with his debts with others
跟他的債跟其他人競爭性高低
how will it develop
會怎麼發展
I really want to see you again
我覺得真的是要再看到
Only ten years later will we really know
十年後才會真正的知道
But that is to say, it can be seen that for us in Taiwan
不過就是說可以看得到對我們台灣而言
When we divide it into private colleges most people practice
當我們把它分成私立大學大多數人去練
General National Universities vs. Top Universities
一般國立大學跟頂尖大學
You can see his way out is different
你可以看到他的出路是不太一樣的
So this article is mainly about this
所以這篇最主要是要講這個
That's the last topic
那最後一個題目啦
Marriage and childbirth of the younger generation
年輕世代的婚姻生育
We have this issue of premarital sex and cohabitation
我們有這個婚前性關係跟同居的題目
In fact, TYP may also be the first in Taiwan to do research
其實TYP也是可能台灣第一個做調查研究
Because these self-administered questionnaires
因為這些用自填問卷的方式
Ask some intimate questions about our sealed questionnaire
就我們有個密封的問卷問一些私密性問題
that's because of these
那因為這些
These samples have been with us for more than ten years
這些樣本都已經跟著我們十多年了
So he should have some trust in us
所以他對我們應該有一定的信任
So they can fill out some smuggling questions themselves
所以他們就可以自己填一些私運性問題
then we also want to know
那我們也想要知道
How does it affect the degree of marital satisfaction of married young couples
影響以婚年輕夫妻婚姻滿意的程度是怎麼樣
Then let me show you the status of the marriage.
那這個就給大家看一下婚姻的狀況
about the information we collect
就我們蒐集的資料
simply speaking
簡單來講
7% married by age 25
在25歲的時候7%結婚
20% at age 28
28歲的時候20%
40% by 2017
到了2017年有40%
I just said that it is consistent with the government's data
我剛剛講過說跟那個政府的資料是吻合的
Let's count the number of people who got married
我們去算那個結婚的人數
Probably using the government's ratio to calculate, there is only a difference of five or six.
大概用政府的比例去算只差五六個而已
So there is 60%
那所以有60%
Still unmarried at an average age of 31
在平均31歲的時候還沒有結婚
So
那麼
So the younger generation has premarital sex
所以年輕世代婚前性關係
let's just say when did you start
我們就說你開始是什麼時候開始的
when was the first time
第一次是什麼時候
let's ask this question first
我們就先問這個問題
Then want to know how your family and peers influence you
然後想要知道家庭跟同儕對你影響是怎麼樣
that with or without premarital sex
那有婚前或無婚前性關係
What is its long-term effect
它長期效果又是如何
We have a group of colleagues who are very concerned about this topic
我們有一組同仁都很關心這個題目
Then the individual and various contextual factors
那麼個人跟各種脈絡的因素
It is also what we want to discuss, explain and clarify
也是我們想要去探討 去解釋 去釐清的
Then this is a one-off survey.
那這個就是一次性的調查
For example, our 2017
比方說我們2017年
Let's just say have you ever had premarital sex?
我們就說你有沒有婚前性關係
Then you will probably find that there are so many
那大概會發現說是這麼多
That is to say, you can see that the jump is very fast.
就說可以看到跳得非常的快
Then I will ask our assistant to do it this afternoon.
那我就今天下午就拜託我們助理特別做一下
Because 60% of us are not married, right?
我們因為有六成的人沒有結婚嘛 對不對
Among these unmarried samples
那這些未婚樣本當中
How did his sexual relationship, premarital intimacy develop?
他的性關係 婚前親密關係又是怎麼發展的
you can see it
你可以看得到喔
We had a group ask him how many of you have never had a boyfriend or girlfriend
我們有一組人問他你從未交過男女朋友的有多少個
There are 302
有302個
There are almost men and women here
這裡面男女差不多了
Have you never had sex before?
你從來沒有性經驗的呢
girls taller
女生高一點
So is this group of nerds and nerds in our hearts?
所以這批是不是我們心中的宅男宅女
31 years old never handed in never nothing
31歲了 從來沒交過 從來沒有什麼什麼什麼
sexual experience
性經驗
so we went to see him
所以我們就去看他的
The effect of the context and the effect of the peers are found
脈絡的效果跟同儕的效果 就發現
If you are in school itself is a protection
你如果是在學校本身是個保護
if you have community involvement you will lower your voice rate
你有社區參與的 你就會降低你的發聲率
But if you're dating or have we asked you to mention
可是如果你有約會對象 或者我們有沒有問你提說
Do you think your good friend has premarital sex? Some people talk about good friends without talking about themselves
你覺得你的好朋友有沒有婚前性關係 有的人不講自己就講好朋友
Those who have good friends are more likely to happen.
那好朋友有的人 他果然比較可能發生
So he thinks he is serious
所以他覺得他是從重行為
Then we can see
然後我們可以看到
Therefore, the experience of premarital sex and cohabitation does increase premarital restoration and early marriage
所以婚前性行為跟同居的經驗的確是增加婚前還原跟早婚
This is the research just done on behalf of Professor Tweety
這就是剛剛代翠兒教授做的研究
Then I'll tell you something funny
那我接下來就講個好玩的給大家聽
We have a very talented colleague who unfortunately left academia Mr. Li Ruizhong
我們有一個很有才華的同仁 可惜離開學術界 李睿忠老師
When he came to join our group, he said he was going to do a lab problem
他來參加我們這組的時候 他說他要做個實驗題
In this experiment, one is five questions, and the other is one more question.
這個實驗題就是一個是五題 一個是多一題
It can be seen from that question
從那一題中可以看出來
did he have premarital sex
他有沒有婚前性關係
As a result, I found that the experimental results of males are about 22 and 3
結果我發現男性的實驗結果大概是22跟3
female is 35
女性是35
But when our research report asked him to self-report
可是當我們的研究報告叫他自我報告的時候
46 for men and 33 for women
男性是46 女性是33
Women's experiments are very similar to self-reports
女性的實驗跟自我報告是非常相近的
Boys will touch, right?
男生會碰碰 對不對
Because he has some peer pressure, right?
因為他有一些同儕的壓力嘛 對不對
i think this is so funny
我覺得這個是太有趣了
I didn't even think they should be 20 years old at that time
我都沒想到那個時候應該他們是20歲
is it 22
是不是 22
i don't know i was at the time
我不知道 我自己在那時候
I think this is so interesting
我覺得這個太有意思了
It's a pity I didn't write it out
可惜沒有寫出來
I think this thing is still very interesting
我覺得這個東西還是很有意思
Although men have about 2.1 times the
雖然男性大概有2.1倍的
will explode his incidence rate
會高爆他的發生率
But the female way of reporting is more reliable.
可是女性的那個報告方式比較可靠
So you get what I mean
這樣你們帶懂我的意思了
this is fun
這個是好玩的
Okay, I'm going to be Professor Yang Wenshan next.
好 接下來在做楊文山教授
Also our mortal colleagues
也是我們的殊死的同仁
cohabitation experience
他就研究同居經驗
His topic is very clear
他題目非常明確
What is the general rate of cohabitation?
同居的普習率大概是怎麼樣
What is his staged development?
他的階段性的發展是怎麼樣
between gender and education
性別跟教育之間
Does the difference matter
差異有沒有影響
Because we talked about premarital sex just now
因為剛才婚前性關係有講到
you learn again
你再學的
In fact, no longer learn to enter the social work
其實不再學進入社會工作的
Less likely to have premarital sex
比較不可能有婚前性關係
So school seems to be a protective factor
所以學校好像是一個保護因子
what about cohabitation
那麼同居又如何呢
He tracked all the way from the age of 24 to 34
他就從24到34歲一路追蹤
Cumulative distance of cohabitation
同居的累積距離
everyone can see
大家可以看得到
at the age of 24
24歲的時候
About 6% for men
男性大概是6%
7% for women
女性是7%
slowly
慢慢的生
By the time of 27 28
到了27 28的時候
women are even slightly taller
女性甚至稍微高一點
right
對不對
but in the end
可是到最後
Men will be higher than women
男性會高於女性
This is traced all the way down
這是一路追蹤下來的
cumulative cohabitation rate
累積的同居率
If you use this to see
如果用這個來看
You can see about half of what didn't happen
你可以看到沒有發生的大概是一半
that this has happened
那這個已經發生
women than men
女性比男性
women are red
女性是紅的
slightly higher
稍微高一點
but later on
可是到後來呢
until the age of 4
到再4歲的時候
male taller
男性更高
Then look at his
然後再看他的
education level
教育程度
in the case of
如果是
below high school
高中以下
college and university
專科的跟大學的
You will find that the less educated the more likely
你會發現教育程度越低越可能
There is a chance of this cohabitation
有這個同居的機率
But after college
可是到了大學以後
The difference between men and women is not that big
男女的差別就不是那麼大
On the gender difference
就性別的差異到了
There are gender differences between men and women beyond college
有大學以上的男女性別的差異
not so big
就不是那麼大了
So overall
所以這樣綜合來看
Our current young generation in Taiwan
我們這個台灣當前年輕世代
What is premarital intimacy really like?
婚前親密關係到底是怎麼樣
I think premarital sex is fairly common
我想婚前性關係相當普遍
young adult
年輕成人
About 80% said he had this experience
大約有八成說他有這個經驗
while studying or not
而在學與否
There is also a significant influence of peers
還有同才的影響很顯著
Second cohabitation is going up with age
第二個同居是會隨著年齡而上升
About 50% said they had lived together
約有五成說他曾經同居過
males outnumber females
其中男性大於女性
while the lower degree of university sex
而大學程度較低性別
People with a university degree will be lower
大學程度人會比較低
Then the sex difference will also decrease
然後性別差異也會減小
So if this thing gives us an inspiration
所以如果這個東西給我們的一個啟發
As far as we're talking about marriage, it's obvious
就我們現在在講結婚結婚很明顯
Not for lack of intimacy
並不是因為缺乏親密關係
but other economic
而是有其他經濟
social considerations
社會各方面的考量
So I'm going to tell you
所以下面我會跟大家講
Some of the results we found with the directization study
我們用直化研究發現的一些結果
but there is one
可是有一個
One thing I find interesting is
有一個東西我覺得有趣的是
60% of unmarried
六成未婚者中
Nearly no intercourse Asexual relationship
近半無交往無性關係
This batch of slaughtering women is really worth noting
這批宰然宰女實在是值得注意
Because her number is not so small
因為她的人數並不是那麼少
good
好
Over the years we have
接下來我們這些年來
I've been doing sex interviews
都一直在做婚禦直性的訪談
There are early marriages and ordinary marriages
有早婚的有普通結婚的
unmarried
有未婚的
Let's talk about early marriage and low education
再講早婚的學歷低
and may have cohabitation experience
而且可能有同居的經驗
so straight interview
那麼直性訪談
We are in April this year
我們在今年4月
also reported last year
去年也報告過
What are the factors that affect early marriage
就是影響早婚的因素有哪些
can be roughly divided into three categories
大致可以分成三大類
Xiao Zhi I don't miss you see for yourself
小致我不念你自己看
Poor family relationship
原生家庭關係不佳
That means she doesn't have a good relationship with her previous generation of parents.
就是說她跟上一代父母關係不佳
or the relationship between the parents
或者是父母之間關係不合
What we just said affects
我們剛剛講的都會影響
and native family
還有原生家庭
bad economic situation
經濟狀況不佳
so through marriage
所以要透過結婚
escape from family of origin
逃離原生家庭
This is the first one I mentioned just now
這個把剛剛我提的第一個
avoid or need a
avoid或者是需要一個
A relationship is put in it
一個關係都放在裡面了
The other is the influence of traditional cultural norms
另外一個是傳統文化規範的影響
especially married by decree
尤其是奉旨成婚
Or want to have children before getting married
或者是想要有小孩才結婚
or have lived together for a long time
或者已經同居很久了
Parents tell him to legalize
父母叫他要合法化
finally i saw one
總算我看到了一個
I think it's normal
我覺得比較正常的
impulse to love
戀愛的衝動
right
對不對
also have
也有
At that time, when I fell in love to a certain extent, I wanted to get married.
就那時候戀愛到一個程度就想結婚
You'd feel like seeing a marriage like this
你會覺得看到這樣的結婚
just breathed a sigh of relief
就鬆了一口氣
this is a comparison
這是一個比較
Everyone will feel more
大家會覺得比較
result of relaxation
放鬆的結果
so unmarried
那麼未婚
we are now in
我們現在最近都在
reasons for engaging in unmarried
從事未婚的原因
Probably can be divided into several
大概也可以分成幾個
just now we said
剛剛我們說
This is because traditional norms influence
這個是因為傳統規範影響
right
對不對
you were married by decree
你奉旨成婚
or how
或者是怎樣
but in this place
可是在這個地方
It is also to challenge the traditional culture
也是要挑戰傳統文化
i don't want to get married
我不要進入婚姻
can also support yourself
也可以養活自己
I don't want to
我不想為了
offspring to marry
繁衍後代而來結婚
so he wants to be unmarried
所以他要未婚
The second one has a poor relationship with the original family
第二個跟原生家庭關係不佳
Especially the relationship between parents
尤其父母之間關係不合
Ladies and gentlemen, this coincides with the love study I just talked about.
各位這跟剛剛我講的戀化研究不謀而合
If there is conflict between parent and child
如果親子之間有衝突
Instead, he'll seek marriage and run away from the family.
他反而會找婚 逃離家庭
When witnessing conflict between parents, especially as a teenager
當尤其青少年期目睹父母之間的衝突
often lowers him to get married
常常降低他要結婚
Some thoughts on starting a family or having children
要成立家庭或生育的一些看法
So our straightening and brightening here is completely consistent with the
所以我們直化亮化在這裡是完全一致的符合的
There are several other reasons
另外還有幾個原因
Lack of incentives to enter married life
缺乏進入婚姻生活的誘因
I've been thinking about this for a long time, what should I do?
這個東西我就想了半天這怎麼辦
and feelings that value stable relationships
和重視穩定交往的感情
better than getting married
勝過結婚
Often he says he already has this partner
常常他說已經有這個伴侶
Seven years, eight years, nine years, ten years
有了七年八年九年十年
just never thought of getting married
就是沒有想到結婚
This is quite common among young people in Taiwan
這個在台灣現在年輕時代相當普遍
Or married life is not free
或者說婚姻生活就是不自由
The marriage process is fast and troublesome
婚姻過程麻利麻煩的
we'll be fine
我們就這樣就好了
How many people will there be
那這一批人會有多少
how much influence will he have
他的影響力會有多大
Must wait until even we go to visit
一定要等到甚至我們去訪問
Several people said that they were supposed to be pregnant.
幾位就說假定真的懷孕了
that must be married
那一定會結婚了
Then you are not pregnant yet
那現在就還沒有懷孕
So the wedding package still exists
所以婚禦包裹還是繼續存在的
There are also people who are more obvious
還有也有人比較明顯的
Not many people are usually willing to say this
這個通常肯這樣講的人都不多
because we even in quantitative research
因為我們甚至在量化研究中
what do you think your ideal partner is
你認為理想伴侶是什麼
will check the economic clear
會勾選經濟清
Whatever condition is good is not the highest
什麼條件好的都不是最高的
We all get along and talk like this
都是合得來有話談這樣子
I think it's not easy to talk all the time in marriage
我想結婚一直談話也不容易
Another one is
另外一個就是
He said that his love experience and dating partner are not suitable
他說戀愛經驗和交往對象都不適合
or a bad love experience
或者是不好的戀愛經驗
Or he thinks the partner is not suitable for marriage
或他認為交往對象不適合進入婚姻
only good for friends
只適合當朋友
But on the other hand we see
可是另外一方面我們看到
It was also stated in these interviews
這些訪問中也有人說
i will get married in a year or two
我一兩年內就會結婚
ask him why
問他為什麼
He said it was because I was of marriageable age
他說是因為我到了適婚年齡
So I think we actually have a chance
所以我想我們其實要有機會
to think young
要有年輕時代認為
what is the marriageable age
適婚年齡是什麼
we asked some questions
我們有問過一些問題
At what age do you think you should get married
你覺得幾歲應該結婚
at what age should we start a family
幾歲應該成家
When he found out that he was 25 years old, he said 28
發現25歲的時候他就說28
When he was 28, he said 32
28的時候他就說32
just go all the way back
就一路往後延
This is also very honest
這也是滿老實的啦
Because it's over, what do you want?
因為已經過了嘛 你要怎樣
so say
那所以說
But the social norm of starting a family
可是成家立業的社會規範
does still exist
的確還是存在的
So the last subtitle
所以最後一個子題
I told everyone
我跟大家報告的
marital satisfaction for young couples
就是年輕夫妻的婚姻滿意
because we have now spoken
因為我們現在已經講了
40% of people are married
有四成的人已經結婚了
Among the 31-year-old married people
那這一批31歲已婚的人當中
Of course this includes his age of 25 and 28
當然這裡面包括他25 28歲
all married people
都已經結婚的人
their marriage is happy
他們的婚姻滿意
what kind of influence
都是受到什麼樣的影響
Will it be the same as before
跟我們以前會不會一樣
you thought you said the same
你以為以前一樣說
You should be satisfied with Ike Arikawa
你有池有川就應該很滿意了
what do they think
他們是怎麼想的
so what do i think about this thing
那麼我想這個東西呢
We just want to see it from different sides
我們就想從不同的面向去看它
Then this article will also be published in October
那這篇文章也是10月會出版的
simply speaking
簡單來講
If you were to explain marital satisfaction
如果你要解釋婚姻滿意
Like I said, there are too many times
就像我講的那時代太多了
It is really difficult to try my best to get rid of the pure scriptures
實在是要想盡辦法去無純經弄很困難
Too many life stages are a thing
太多生命階段是一件事情
On the psychological level, your mother-in-law and daughter-in-law in childhood are all here
你心理層面兒童期婆媳等等都在這裡
personal reason
個人因素
Family Economic Factors This is a set
家庭經濟因素這是一套
In addition, you can say that relational factors
另外你可以說關係性因素
For example, if there is a lack of communication between newlyweds
例如新婚夫妻之間如果缺乏溝通
Poor relationship between parent and adult child
父母和成年子女之間關係不好
This will affect the marital satisfaction of young couples
這會都會影響年輕夫妻的這個婚姻滿意
In addition, many people in the West do gender role attitudes
另外在西方很多人做性別角色態度
think a person if gender role attitudes
認為一個人如果性別角色態度
Believe that men and women should be more equal
認為男女應該越平等
the better his marriage
他婚姻關係越佳
But on the other hand, it is also found that husbands and wives compare
可是另外一方面也發現丈夫跟妻子來比
If the wife has higher gender role attitudes than the husband
如果妻子的性別角色態度比丈夫高
More equality is more detrimental to marriage satisfaction
平等很多反而越不利於婚姻的滿意
This goes back to the structural differences we talk about in sociology
這就回到我們社會學講的結構性的差異了
This is an attitude difference
這個是態度性的差異
If there is too much difference between husband and wife
如果夫妻之間差別太大
Usually he is not easy
通常他比較不容易
easy to produce good results
容易產生好的效果
What's the difference between east and west
東西方又有什麼不一樣
The West will refer to research in recent years
西方會提到近年來的研究
will speak between spouses
會說到配偶之間
The importance of family factors
跟家庭因素的重要性
think marital relationship
認為婚姻關係
Husbands and wives feel differently
丈夫和妻子有不同的感受
you can't just use one person
你不能只用一個人
so we are lucky
所以我們很幸運
We ask the master sample again
我們又問主樣本
asked his spouse
又問他的配偶
on the same topic
對同樣的題目
The two of them can have different answers
他們兩個人可以有不同的回答
in addition
另外
There are also differences in resources between husbands
丈夫間的資源也有差異
There are also differences in the feeling of marriage relationship
婚姻關係感受也有差異
it's all western research
這都是西方研究
tell us what we should pay attention to
告訴我們應該注意的
But in our Eastern social context
可是在我們東方的社會脈絡中
our patrilineal society
我們父系社會
Marriage was never a matter of two young people
婚姻從來不是兩個年輕人的事情
it is a union of two families
它是兩個家庭的結合
So our previous
所以我們以前的
not talking about marriage
不是講說結婚
It's about marrying a daughter-in-law
是講娶媳婦
marry a wife because
娶媳婦是因為
Are you going to take a female
你是要把一個女性
marry into this family
娶到這個家庭來
Then in this cultural context
那麼在這一個文化脈絡中
The relationship between mother-in-law and daughter-in-law is a good study
婆媳關係是個很好的研究
We are in this year's survey of seniors
我們在這個今年的老人調查
We'll do some questions specifically on this
我們就會特別針對這方面做一些問題
Then exchange relatives with the three generations of the same family, etc.
然後向三代同堂帶接交換親戚等等
Simply put, our argument is
簡單來講我們的argument就是說
The current family system in Taiwan is a modified
台灣的這個目前的家庭體系是一個修正式的
matriarchal family system
婦系家庭體系
In this system, cultural norms follow the genealogy of whether you are husband or wife
在這個體系當中文化規範跟你是夫或妻這個系譜
is very important
是非常重要的
Therefore, the direct interaction must include structural relations and normative aspects.
所以帶接的互動必須包括結構關係跟規範等面向
Study on the Core Keys of Marriage Satisfaction in Taiwan
研究台灣婚姻滿意核心關鍵
In fact, raising it a level or two is to ask this sentence
其實把它上升一兩層就是問這句話
Does Feminine Culture Persist? Or Has It Changed?
到底婦系文化持續存在嗎?還是它已經改變了
So if a marriage is not two parties but a union of two families
所以如果婚姻不是兩個當事人而是結合兩個家庭的話
Then marital satisfaction is not a feeling between two people
那麼婚姻滿意也不是兩個人之間的感受
It involves different inputs between the family level and the network of relatives and friends
它涉及家庭層次跟親友網絡之間不同的投入
OK, so we use
好 那我們用的就是
2014 and 2015 Spouse Survey
2014跟2015的配偶調查
As a result, this thing may not be seen
結果這個東西大概看不到
But basically a happy marriage
不過基本上來講婚姻滿意
Everyone is satisfied
大家都還算滿意
So this means that you and
那麼這個就是說你跟
Mother-in-law relationship or relationship with parents-in-law
婆媳關係或者是跟岳父母關係
You can see it roughly here
你可以看得到大概在這裡
Then we also constructed
然後我們也建構了
Did you live with your parents after you got married?
你結婚後有沒有跟父母同住
with my husband a lot
跟夫方很多
Then the second is to live separately
然後第二是分住
The third is the right way
第三的才是其方
Also this thing took some effort
另外這個東西花了一些力氣
we bring them to exchange
我們把他們帶接的交換
In financial terms
用財務金錢來看的話
one is equal
有一種是平等的
one is western
一個是偏西方
one is partial husband
一個是偏夫方
result
結果咧
We take the whole model
我們把整個模型
Divided into two categories of self-disguised phases
分成兩大類的自變相來看
The first category is called resources
第一類叫做資源
that includes these
就是包括這些都是
family income etc.
家庭收入等等
Wife is more educated
妻子教育比較高
Spouses are separated by resources
配偶衝隔的都是資源
The other category we call cultural norms
另外一類我們把叫做文化規範
you can see it here
這裡面你可以看得到
Cultural norms have to live with
文化規範有同住
There is a yin and qing relationship and a connection
有陰青關係有帶接
exchange etc.
交換等等
you can see the wife is affected
你可以看到妻子受到影響
very big
特別大
I list the notable ones
我把顯著的列出來
not listed
不顯著就不列
It also affects the husband
對丈夫也有影響
For example, living with the husband
例如跟夫方同住相比
Husbands who live apart are more satisfied
分住的丈夫比較滿意
but the interesting thing is
可是有趣的是
Compared with living with Husband Fang
跟夫方同住相比
the few who live with their wives
跟妻方同住的少數的那些
it's less
這是比較少的
The wife is dissatisfied
太太是比較不滿意的
so again
所以再一次
I found that at different stages
我就發現在不同階段中
unconventional atypical arrangement
非傳統非典型的安排
often lead to negative effects
常常導致負面的效果
This quantitative research can be said here
這量化研究可以講到這裡
Why
為什麼
May need some straightforward additions
可能就需要一些直化的補充
on the other hand
另外一方面
we found westward
我們發現偏西方
yes can bring some benefits
是可以帶來一些好處
but negative relationship
可是陰性關係
very important
非常的重要
Husband thinks he is with
丈夫覺得他跟
The more women get along with the mother
越婦越母相處
have some pressure
有一些壓力
or when he feels less than ideal
或他覺得不太理想的時候
he is
他的確是
no matter husband or wife
不管丈夫或太太
are equally affected
都同樣受到影響
But for the wife
可是對太太來講
When he has problems with his in-laws
他跟公公婆婆有問題的時候
he will be affected
他才會受到影響
So the conclusion of this study
所以這個研究他的結論
just tell us
就是跟我們說
Let's look at it theoretically
我們從理論上來看
Actually resources and cultural norms
其實資源和文化規範
will have an important impact
都會產生重要的影響
And we are doing some further analysis
而我們在進一步的一些分析
I didn't release it here
我這裡沒有放出來的
That is, the cultural norm is that wives are happy in marriage.
就是說文化規範對妻子婚姻滿意
I just said
剛剛我講了
it makes a big impact
它造成很大的衝擊
However, if we further de-interact
可是如果進一步去交互作用
It was discovered that she was living with her husband's parents
發現是跟夫方父母同住
And she's a full-time working wife
而且自己是全職工作的妻子
The most obvious impact
影響最為明顯
It is most likely to have negative effects
它最可能造成負面的影響
That's it
這樣子講好了
So if the wife here is working full time
所以在座如果太太是全職工作
Because I live with my husband's parents
因為跟夫方父母同住
Pay more attention to give more support
比較注意要多給支持
Then if the husband feels negative
然後丈夫如果感受到負面的
Negative relationship will lead to both husband and wife
陰性關係就會導致夫妻雙方
Negative Effects of Marital Satisfaction
婚姻滿意的負面效果
So what is the reflection of this thing for me?
所以這個東西給我的反思是什麼
Taiwanese family
台灣的家庭
In fact, many places are still traditional
其實很多地方還是在傳統
The impact with the modern
跟現代之間的衝擊
pick there
在那裡挑
and compromise and make some responses
和妥協跟做出一些因应的一些反应
because of our values
因为我们的价值观
some of our actions are continuous
我们的行为之间有一些是持续的
some are constant
有些是不变的
So if Taiwan still has an East Asian society
所以如果说台湾还有东亚社会
We are different from Europe and the United States
我们跟欧美地区不一样的地方
because you study a family in transition
在于你研究一个变迁中的家庭
Needs to go beyond your interpretation of personal resources
需要在你解释个人资源之外
The interaction of cultural norms should also be considered
应该要同时考量文化规范的交互作用
I also believe that this is our social science community in Taiwan.
我也相信这是我们台湾社会科学界的
Family studies can be done internationally in academia
家庭研究可以在国际的学术界
where you can make a little contribution
可以做一些些许贡献的地方
Because instead of just applying some western theories
因为与其只是套用西方的一些理论
resource theory
他们就是资源论
what kind of resources
怎么样的资源
When we add the importance of cultural norms
我们把文化规范的重要性加进去的时候
they will find
他们会发现
At least in this large area with a large population
至少在人口很众多的这一大块地方
it's very important
它是非常重要的事情
There are already so many slopes in our current data release
我们现在的资料释出已经有这么多坡了
Welcome everyone to apply with the research office to use
欢迎大家跟调研室申请去使用
20 years
20年來
Then we also published two books in English
然後我們也出過兩本英文的專書
Now our second English book
現在我們第二本英文專書
in preparation probably there will be
正在預備中大概會有
16 to 18 papers for Phase 2 results
16到18篇針對第二階段的結果
then in the end i was
那最後我是
thank you very much
真的非常感謝
most grateful
最感謝的
They are all samples of our young people
都是我們的這些年輕人的樣本
They are willing to continue to be us
他們願意持續的被我們
visit for more than an hour every time
訪問一個多鐘頭每一次
200 yuan
200塊
Very sorry
很不好意思
Then
然後
and our parents
還有我們的家長們
Especially this year we are going to
尤其今年我們要進行
Sixth Wave 62-Year-Old Parents Study
第六波62歲家長的研究
I don't know how many parents
我不知道還有多少家長
willing to answer
願意回答
But at least in the first five waves
可是至少在前五波
we are very grateful to them
我們非常感謝他們
then this year we will try
那今年我們會嘗試
That is, outside of one of the parents
就是說在家長之一之外
another one
另外一位
We also do a short roll of visits
我們也做一個短卷的訪問
hope that the relationship between parents
希望可以把父母之間的
problems condensed together
問題一起濃縮起來
The teacher and principal of the junior high school
當年國中的老師校長
Especially middle school teachers
尤其國中老師
can you imagine
你們能想像嗎
I took the entrance exam in July and June
七月六月考了聯考
September asked him what his test score was
九月問他考幾分
He told you to forget
他都跟你說忘記
Fortunately, we asked the teacher
然後還好我們那時候問老師
teachers have records
老師都有 老師都有記錄
So we use the teacher
所以我們是用老師
So these kids are very prosperous
所以這些小孩 旺性很高
Then, I really want to thank these principals
然後 也真是謝謝這些校長
Except for one, he said he had a heart for the job, and he didn't answer.
除了一位 他說他心上任 他不回答
In fact, each of his principals is interested in community resources.
其實他每一個校長 都對社區資源
How does the school respond to these needs?
學校怎麼樣因應這些需要改變
Give us some good information
都給我們很好的一些資料
We are also very grateful to all the guides and interviewers
我們也特別謝謝所有的讀導跟訪員們
I think there is something in it today
我想今天有一些在當中
This is a special thank you to everyone
這是要特別謝謝大家
If it weren't for you to go this way one by one
如果沒有你們一題一題的這樣去
If you look at it, we have too many messages and can’t do it
看的話 我們太多Message都沒有辦法做
it's really not easy
這真的是非常不容易
Moreover, our guides and interviewers are carefully selected.
而且 我們讀導 訪人都是精挑細選的
special thanks
特別謝謝
We also thank all participating research colleagues
我們也感謝所有參與的研究同仁
There are quite a few of them today
今天有好幾位在當中
There are people before and after us
我們之前之後都還有一些人
Especially our former and former research assistants
尤其我們前後任研究助理
with all our postdocs
跟我們的所有的博士後
We originally said that from the first generation
我們本來說從第一代
How many generations of research assistants have there been
一直到現在已經有多少代的研究助理了
We're all going from middle age to old age too.
我們也都從中年變老年了
We would like to thank the Chinese
我們要特別感謝中華
Deputy Director Nakazonozono
中園園院方副院長
There are also social institutes
還有社會所
Especially the administrative colleagues are too busy to help
尤其行政同仁幫助太多忙
such a big study
這麼大的研究
You can imagine how complicated he is
你可以想得到他有多麼複雜
The Ministry of Science and Technology of the National Science Council has also supported it all the way to this day
國科會科技部也是一路支持到今天
thank you all
謝謝大家
Thank you very much Professor Ying
非常謝謝這影教授
very brilliant and interesting research
非常精采而有趣的研究
Absolutely worthy of our hospital's strong support
絕對值得我們院方大力的支持
what about now
那現在呢
We will open this time to all listeners
我們就把這個時間開放給各位聽眾
Let's see if you have any questions
那看各位有沒有什麼想提問
We are now open to everyone
我們現在就開始開放給大家
ok sir
好,這位先生
Come on
來一聲
ask the professor
請教一下教授
The new syllabus we are now implementing
我們現在實行的新課綱
Right, starting this year
是吧 今年開始
a child of christ
那對基督的一個兒童
and adult
以及成年
parents
做父母親的
do grandparents
做阿公阿嬤的
How to express the country's new curriculum
如何來示意國家的新課綱
Empower children to compete in entering
使兒童在進入的競爭能力上
Won't
不會
Lack
缺少
Thanks
謝謝
You're younger and I can't get mad
你比較年輕 我這氣不起來
besides
還有
Collect some topics together
一起收集一些題目
Let Professor Ying answer him together
讓影教授一起回答他
Are there any other questions?
還有沒有其他的問題
Will it make a difference for me to say that?
對 我這樣講是不是會有影響
Okay, thank you
好 謝謝
This question about the new syllabus
這個有關新課綱的問題
because it happened in recent years
因為是近年來發生
We did it in 2000
我們是2000年做的嘛
So at that time for us it was
所以那個時候對我們來說是
From joint examination system to
從聯考制變成
partial application
部分的申請制
So education reform attendance is in that place
所以教育改革的出席是在那個地方
so we didn't touch the new syllabus
所以我們並沒有涉及新課綱
should say like this
應該這樣子講
It should be said that the advantages of TYP are
那應該講TYP的優點是
At that time, it can still be approved by the principal
那個時候還可以經過校長同意
Education Bureau agrees
教育局同意
we can do a whole class survey
我們就可以做全班的調查
now includes DH several years ago
現在包括衛生署好幾年前
Did you hear they're going to do a class survey?
是不是聽說他們要去做全班調查
subject to parental consent
都要經過父母同意
The sample of that thing is not right anytime soon
那東西樣本馬上就不對了
Then it becomes what we call deviation
那就變我們叫偏差的
Yes or no
是不是
Is BioS biased?
BioS偏差嗎
not a biased sample
不是偏頗的樣本
biased sample words
偏頗的樣本的話
It is not suitable for us to do these studies
就不適合我們做這些研究
so we are lucky
所以我們算是幸運的
Then about education reform
那麼有關教育改革
Between the new system and the inauguration
新制跟就職之間
The information we can provide is
我們能夠提供的訊息就是
what we just said
剛剛我們講的
The new system brings more obvious
新制是帶來比較明顯的
social class inequality
社會階級的不平等
That is, I just had
也就是我剛剛有
sorry i just repeat
對不起 我就重複
that is
就是說
twenty five percent
百分之二十五
Households in the top 25 percent of income
前百分之二十五收入的家庭
Chances for his children to attend star high schools
他的子女上明星高中的機會
very significantly high
非常顯著的高
So this is probably what we can think of here
所以這個大概是我們可以想到這裡的
Then admit the sample before merging
然後承認樣本合併之前
We have found that the combination of these two groups of samples probably has no major problems in other aspects
我們有發現這兩組樣本合併大概在其他方面沒有太大問題
so we just merge it
所以我們就把它合併
The new curriculum must follow
那新客剛一定是要跟
Only recently started to matter
最近才開始做的才有關係
just we
就我們就
These samples are all too old to be 31 years old
這些樣本都太老了都31歲
Hehehe
呵呵呵
but thank you for asking
不過謝謝你提問
Hello Professor
教授你好
Thank you very much for your efforts
很謝謝你們的努力
i want to ask a question
我想請問個問題
Because I think you are very concerned about this so-called vulnerable group
因為我想你們就是很關心這個所謂的弱勢族群
I think we have what's called affectionate disorder
我想我們有一個就是所謂深情障礙的
such a person
這樣人
During the whole development process, he didn't know if there was any in you
他在整個發展過程不知道你這裡面有沒有
especially to track or say
特別去追蹤或者說
you on this
你對這個
you
你們
do you have any such a plan
你們有沒有什麼這樣的一個計劃
Some simple assessments can be made on this scene in Taiwan
對對這個台灣的現場可以做一些簡單的評估
or
或是說
right
對
Thank you for your question
謝謝您的提問
us
我們
Generally speaking, we take the hospital of traditional Chinese medicine to be responsible for promoting another big investigation
通常來講我們以中醫院負責推動另外一個大調查
From the survey of social change in Taiwan
台灣社會變遷調查來講
Before I borrowed time, we all had special inquiries about the need for some disabled people in the family.
我藉時間前我們都有特別問家庭中需要有一些身心障礙的
That number is usually too small in the overall survey
那個人數通常都過分的少在整個大調查當中
Based on our own survey
以我們自己大調查來講
Why did I specifically mention deviant behavior
我剛剛為什麼特別提偏差行為
because that's what we can gather
因為這是我們可以收集到的資料
we have noticed
我們有注意到有
I don't know if you guys really remember
當時我不知道各位老實在記不記得
At that time, I will say that our English is called
那時候我再說我們英文叫
Taiwan Youth Survey
台灣 Youth Survey
Don't talk about Taiwan Youth Project
你們都不要說台灣 Youth Project
I said I don't want because we have no strength
我說我不要因為我們沒有力氣
we don't have social workers
我們沒有社工
And we don't have a counselor
然後我們也沒有心理輔導老師
If you need psychological counseling
如果遇到有心理輔導需要的
what do we do when the parents call
父母會打電話來的我們怎麼辦
But everyone was young back then
可是那時候大家都很年輕嘛
Everyone says they want to
都人小至氣高都說要
so i remember i was serious so
所以我記得我還很認真的因此
Get to know some psychology of Yilan County
認識了宜蘭縣的一些心理
sorry psychiatrist
對不起精神科醫師
I'll just say we know he has this problem
我就會比方說我們知道他有這個問題
the teacher reacted
老師有反應
I asked the doctor to say
我就請這位醫師說
You can go to this school to help
你可以幫忙到這個學校去幫忙
Then I found out that their school is high school
然後我才知道他們學校高中了而言
their referral
那時候他們的轉介
The referral referral system is not like this
referal轉介的系統不是這樣的
Be sure to contact your tutor with them
一定要輔導老師跟他們聯繫
The hospital can't go there to take the baby away
醫院不能去那裡把孩子帶走的
I also remember
那另外我也記得
A father specifically called to say
有個父親特地打電話來說
why don't you guys visit me this year
你們為什麼今年不來訪問我了
how can i tell him
我怎麼跟他說
Because his son is gone
因為他兒子已經不在了
his son left
他兒子離開了
if his son leaves i want him
如果他兒子離開我還要他
I can't help it
我沒辦法的
I can't get in touch with his son
我他跟他兒子聯不起來
At that time I felt really sad
那時候我心裡真的覺得很難過
then we have some mothers
那我們還有一些母親
also called
也曾經打電話來
Let's just say that the son is the otaku we just talked about
就說兒子就是我們剛剛講的宅男
college graduates do nothing
大學畢業什麼都不動
He said nobody cares
他說誰都不理
but the strange thing is
可是奇怪的是
tip interviewer calls
tip訪員打電話
make an appointment with him
跟他約時間訪問
he said yes
他說好
wow this mama washes out
哇 這個媽媽洗出妄外
called several times and said
打了幾次電話說
can you please
可不可以拜託
just please let him come to your place
就拜託讓他去你們那裡
for free
不要錢
Just when your princess was born
就是當你們的公主生
just let him go
只要讓他走去
Just go out and help
出去家门去帮忙就好
you can see this happening
你可以看到这种情况
few others
他人数很少
we have no way
我们没有办法
as an adult
作为大人
there is no way to track like this
没有办法这样追踪
So I always feel very owed
所以我一直觉得心里很亏欠
Not only research does not know more than the system
不仅在研究上不知道的比制度多
in difficult situations
在遇到困难的情况下
We can't help enough
我们能够帮助的更加的不够
Really are
真的是
So we just hope that at least
所以我们只希望至少
let us know
让我们知道
in deviant behavior
在偏差行为上
They were looked down upon from childhood
他们从小就被看不起的
there is a problem
就有问题的
In fact, he is likely to start a business in the future.
其实他将来是很可能去创业的
So give humanity a little hope
所以给人人性一点希望吧
you don't know
各位也不知道
Are there any other questions?
还有没有其他的问题
good
好
there are several questions here
这里有好几个问题
one two three
一 二 三
from this young man
从这个年轻人开始
hello professor
教授您好
I just want to ask
我想请问一下就是
about teens in
关于青少年在
The part of bullying between the possible fellow
与可能同财之间霸凌的部分
for their growth
會對於他們的成長
Except we usually
除了我們平常就是
Regret that linear thinking may produce
直線性的思考可能會產生的後悔外
Is there anything else that was accidentally discovered in the research?
還有沒有什麼研究上意外發現的一些事情
As for my reporter's answer
就我記者的回答
If I forget, trouble the two teachers to add
如果我忘記麻煩兩位老師補充
I reporter we have had to ask
我記者我們有曾經要問過
a problem called school bullying
叫做校園霸凌的問題
we even then
我們甚至那時候
I still remember if Teacher Yawenshan said
我還記得是不是雅文山老師說
Many junior high school students join gangs
很多國中生去參加黑幫
Do you have
有沒有
At that time, we also followed the newspapers
那時候我們也跟著報紙在講
we also asked
我們也問了
But too few people come out
可是出來的人都太少
because you need to know
因為你要知道
That's not to say too little doesn't matter
這不是說太少就不重要
It's that we have no way to process this data
而是我們沒有辦法處理這個資料
Among your five thousand people
你五千個人當中
For example we even ask
例如我們甚至問
Your first sex was forced
你第一次性行為是被迫的
We also asked this question
我們也問過這個問題
All four thousand people came down
全部四千多人下來
forty eight
四十八個
What about forty-eight if
那對四十八個如果
You're going to do something special that's hard to do
你要去做特別的東西很難做
there is no way
就沒有辦法
48 more than no
48個比不是的
or 48 than yes no
或者48個比有 沒有
This 48 is too small, everything is too small
這48都太小 怎麼樣都太小
So I remember we had this problem
所以我記得我們有出過這個問題
Just asking if you ever joined a gang
就是問說你有沒有加入黑幫
Actually this is
其實 這就是
Sociology is different from journalism
社會學跟新聞學不一樣啦
journalism for this particular
新聞學對這種特殊的
it can write a long article
它就可以寫了一大篇
Makes you feel like everything is in danger, doesn't it?
讓你覺得草木皆兵 對不對
Then we also hope to be able to fight against grass and trees
那我們也很希望能夠對草木皆兵
do a little proof but
做一點證明 可是
Too little data age
資料時代太少
So that school bully you want special sampling
所以那個校園霸凌 你要特殊的抽樣
maybe more likely
也許有比較可能
Because we used to have a part-time assistant
因為我們以前有個兼任助理
Later, at the Chinese University of Hong Kong, those social work doctors
後來在香港中文大學那些社工博士
He can't use TYP
他就沒有辦法用TYP
to do school bullying
去做校園霸凌
Instead, special sampling is required
而必須要特殊的抽樣
Probably so, right?
大概是這樣 對不對
Hello Professor, my problem is more troublesome
教授你好 我的問題比較麻煩
older is
老一點 就是
Our teenagers in Taiwan now
我們現在台灣的青少年
His ingredients may not only be
他的成分 可能也不只是
native of taiwan
台灣的本土的
He may also include family members like outsiders
他可能也包含像有外配家庭
or planning a family
或是規劃家庭
I don't know about you in that regard
那在這方面 我不知道你們
Did you discover something during your process?
你的過程當中是不是有什麼發現
The second is about education
第二個是有關於教育的問題
That's what we did when you started in 2000
就是我們在您從2000年開始做
That was between 2000 and 204 to 2008
那在2000大概204到08中間
Taiwan has already begun to have so-called home education
已經開始台灣有所謂的在家教育
or non-school style education of these families
或是非學校型態的教育這些家庭
I don't know you guys are in the process of adjusting
不知道你們在調整過程當中
Has there been such a case?
有沒有發生這樣的個案
how do you deal with it
那你們怎麼處理
thanks for asking the first question
謝謝你問第一個問題
i wish someone would ask
我就希望有人問
because we had
因為我們那時候有
we spent a month or two
我們花了一兩個月時間
Sort out mother or father
整理出母親或者父親
Children whose place of birth is not in Taiwan
出生地不在台灣的小孩
The result is probably out
結果大概出來
If I remember correctly it is more than 100
我如果沒有記錯是100多個
Then he is almost 60% in the mainland station
那麼其中大陸站他快六成
I thought it was great
那時候我想太好了
We this is the characteristic of our Zhihua sample
我們這是我們直華樣本的特徵
so i remember we were
所以我記得我們就在
A certain area in Donglu, Nanjing
南京東陸某一個地區
ask him to discuss
就約他討
Just interview him and an assistant
就跟他訪談跟一個助理
It's not easy to get a date and I'm happy
很不容易約到很高興
As a result, there is no way to do it
結果一做下去就沒辦法
because we are too early
因為我們太早了
his mother is indonesian
他的媽媽是印尼人
He told me that I was born a few years earlier
他跟我說還好我早生了幾年
At that time my classmates said
那時候我同學都說
your mother is a foreigner
你媽媽是外國人
He said if I was born late
他說如果我晚生了
five years ten years bad
五年十年糟糕了
I became a child of a foreign spouse family
我就變成外配家庭的小孩
my puppet
我小偶
that way
那這樣
Indeed I did not consider the location
的確我沒有考慮到那個地點
That is to say, our entry point is the year 2000
就是說我們的切入點是2000年
even said
竟然說
He was Guoyi at that time
他那時候是國藝
He didn't feel discriminated against
他沒有感受到被歧視
On the contrary, he is very proud in class
反而在班上很神氣
because mom is a foreigner
因為媽媽是外國人
you understand me so well
你這樣懂我意思
So this discriminatory nature of foreign assignments
所以這種對外配的歧視性
Although the number of people who followed him
固然跟著他來的人的數量
and quality
以及質量有關
But it is more of a social ethos
可是更是一個社會的風氣
I always tell you a fact
我一直常常跟大家說一個事實
if we say
我們假如說
Less educated outsiders
外配的教育程度比較低
The education level of the person who begs you to marry him
求你娶他的人教育程度
Is it higher?
是比較高的嗎
It is who in our Taiwanese society marries whom
是我們台灣社會的誰娶誰
so i keep saying
所以我一直說
If the expatriate family comes to Taiwan
外配家庭來我們台灣的話
them
他們
Didn't come to change our family system
並沒有來改變我們的家庭制度
They bring in some new cultural elements
他們帶入一些新的文化的因素
it is possible they are
有可能他們在
Cooking is different
燒飯上面不太一樣
All aspects of diet
飲食各方面
However, the entire family accommodation still maintains considerable integrity.
可是整個家庭住宿還是維持相當的完整性
As for the changes you said after 2008
那至於你說2008年以後的這些改變
Because we've moved beyond that time
由於我們已經超越那個時間了嘛
That is to say, this group of people are all national first or third nationals in 2000.
就是說這一批人都是2000年國一或者國三
Every time we recruit our assistants, we must have such a person
我們收化我們每一次助理都要有這樣的人
we just looked at him thinking we were visiting him
我們就看著他想我們正在訪問他
So Xuanyuan told me that he is the last Guoyi sample
所以宣源跟我說他是最後一個國一的樣本
The next assistants are all smaller than this
接下來的助理都比這個還小了
you can say it like this
可以這樣子講
So we say there's something wrong with them watching him
所以我們說有他們在我們看著他就是出問題
sometimes ask their opinion how they feel
有時候問問他們的意見他們會覺得怎麼樣
The teacher is very interesting
老師滿有意思
Then we're the last one or two
那我們也最後一個兩個
good
好
so
所以
hello i want to ask
你好我想要問一下
That's the one you mentioned about flagging
就是你有提到高片插旗的人
For his subsequent entrepreneurship, he still has a higher income
對於他之後的創業還有收入較高
Ariel mentioned that there is a level of conservatism
阿里爾提到說有一個保守程度
I would like to ask what is discussed in the degree of conservatism
我想問保守程度討論的內容是哪些
Also for entrepreneurship and higher income
還有對於創業和收入較高
Do you have any ideas to explain this?
你們會有什麼想法去解釋這件事情嗎
Conservative attitude
有關保守態度
We have a set of topics
我們是有一組題目
Just ask him what he thinks about some attitudes in society
就是問他對社會上的一些態度的看法
social values
就是社會價值觀
generally speaking
通常來講
Males are more conservative than females
男性一支比女性要保守
less conservative
較以程度低的比較保守
working class more conservative
勞工階級比較保守
This is not a unique phenomenon in Taiwan
這不是我們台灣獨特的現象
the whole world is like this
這全世界都是這樣
So I've been talking about generational differences before
所以以前一直在說世代差異
Recently this John Toppings teacher would say
最近這個John Toppings的老師就會說
He thinks the coming of this generation is a class difference
他覺得這個世代來臨是階級差異
That's not all class differences
那所有的也不是階級差異
Politicians everywhere are eager to stir up class differences too
到處的政客們也都很希望挑起階級差異
Because the class differences are very obvious
因為階級差異是非常明顯的
So I'm thinking that this thing is actually
所以我在想說這個東西其實是
From the perspective of our academic research
從我們學術研究眼光
would not like to see such a development
不會希望看到這樣的發展
Although we will master, record and analyze
雖然我們會掌握會記錄會分析
Then I just said Chen Yi, Mr. Fu
那剛剛我說陳毅 傅老師
I feel very happy that
我覺得很高興的是
This group has always had low family cohesion
這一批一向家庭凝聚力低
High degree from single bird family
來自單禽家庭程度高
low support among friends
朋友之間支持低
And I'm talking about significantly lower
而且我講的都是顯著的低
This group of people until he was 31 years old
這一群人到他31歲的時候
He is more likely to have a higher income
他是收入比較高的可能性高
I think this is an inspiration to everyone
我覺得這是給大家很多的一個激勵
And this is not journalism
而且這個不是新聞學
this is sociology
這是社會學
This is statistically significant
這是統計上顯著的
And this group of people is not so small
而且這一批人並不是那麼少
Only over 9%
只有9%多
don't i think it's very interesting
是不是 我覺得這是非常有意思的
so ask me why
所以聊問我為什麼
That is to say, maybe we are in the process of breaking the impression of the scientific version
就是說可能我們在科版印象的破除上
it may be social science
這可能是社會科學
able to contribute to society and some
能夠有助於社會和一些
a big element
一個很大的一個元素吧
Mr. Zhou Wei
周薇先生
My surname is Fang
我姓方
I am retired from the Institute of Marine Biology, Sun Yat-sen University
我是中山大學海洋生物所退休
I remember personal academic orientation
我記憶個人的學術的方向
It is also closely related to statistics
也是跟統計學有密切的關係
we do a lot
我們做了很多
Statistical work on this reliquary
這個聖物統計方面的工作
Then I congratulate you on this very massive one
那我恭喜你這個非常大規模的一個
A trial protocol and study
一個試驗協議跟研究
What I'm going to say next are some of my thoughts
我下面要講的是我一些感想
Don't dare say it's dialectical or questioning
不敢說是辯證或者是詢問
Because although we are all statistics
因為我們之間雖然都是統計
But I think there are a lot of shocks that are new to me
但是我覺得有很多對我是很新的衝擊
First of all, the sampling of our relic statistics is
那首先我們聖物統計學在取樣上是
There is a stricter specification
有比較嚴密的那個規範
But I see that your database is very large
但是我看你這個database這個非常大
thousands of individual cases
幾千個人案件
And there's about 20 years of
而且還有就是歷時大概有20年
There is no way for us to do such a research
這樣子的一個研究我們是沒有辦法做
Then I just express a little bit of my feelings
那我只是發表一點點我的感想
That's because I don't know much about directness research.
那因為我不是很懂什麼叫直性研究
We compare by measurement, by data
我們是比較用測量、用數據
use the tight one
用很嚴密的那個
Some tests such as variable anti-review
變防溫習之類的一些tests
So I may have some misunderstandings and I'm not sure
所以我可能有一些誤解也收不定
Then my first feeling is
那我第一個感覺是
because you were doing this 20 years ago
因為20年前你在做這個
A sample like this
這樣子的一個抽樣的
When you are going to ask questions and send out questionnaires
你準備要問什麼問題發什麼問卷的時候
but i guess
但是我猜想
the tests you did later
你後來做的那些tests
In fact, it did not take into account when sampling
事實上並沒有當初在抽樣的時候並沒有考慮到
you need to answer so many questions
你需要回答那麼多問題
That is to say, the question you asked later was
也就是說你後來問的問題是
When the questionnaire was unloaded
當初卸劑這個問卷的時候
you actually didn't expect
你事實上是沒有想到的
It was only later from such a large Database
只是後來從那麼大的一個Data base裡面
you generate some motivation
你產生出來一些動機
did some tests
做了一些tests
So here's what we're talking about
所以這就跟我們來講
just might be
就是有可能是
Do you measure first and ask for proof
你是先測量先問證
And then finally some Ni said from it
然後最後才從裡面產生一些尼說
Then come to tests
然後再來tests
This is the same as when we were doing ecology in the wild
這跟我們在做野外做生態的時候
is kind of the opposite
是有點相反的
Because you mentioned that Ni said it would
因為你提出來的尼說會
would in fact be more or less
會事實上是多多少少
Affect your original experimental design
影響到你當初的試驗設計
Include some that are not randomly sampled
包括一些是不是隨機取樣
or something like that
或等等這一類的事情
Then I look at the parsed stuff
然後我看分析的東西
also analyzed many
也分析了很多的
this different ni said
這個不同的尼說
Of course your team is very big
當然你這個team非常大
so there are many
所以有很多
many people doing their own thing
很多人各做各的
So this database cannot be a single database
所以這個database不可能是一個單一的database
So every member of every team
所以每一個team裡面的每一個成員
when he did this test
他做這個test的時候
He screens the data he needs in it
他都在裡面篩選他需要的data
So these data and another team
所以這些data跟另外一個team
In fact, the data made will have some differences
所做的data事實上是會有一些差異的
So it is impossible to have the same database
所以不可能同一個database
do all these quizzes you say
做所有的這些你說的測驗
because if that's the case
因為假如是這樣子的話
If you have to answer so many questions
你要回答那麼多問題的話
We're statistically just going to have less degrees of freedom
我們在統計學上就是自由度會不足
because you have to answer a lot of questions
因為你要回答好多問題
Every time you ask a question, your degree of freedom will be reduced.
你每一個問題你自由度就少掉一些
So even if you have such a large database
所以儘管你有那麼大的一個database
I feel a little lack of freedom
我是有點感覺會不會自由度不足
Another problem is
另外一個問題就是
I've been trying to guess what statistics you use
我一直想要猜想你用的是什麼統計學
I always thought it was because I didn’t understand a lot in the study of direct belief.
我本來一直開始想是在直信研究裡面很多都是我不懂的
So it's probably doing direct research to do the test
所以大概就是在直信研究來做test
But then I made a guess
但是後來我做了一個猜測
You are probably using a method of the so-called maximum likelihood
你用的大概是所謂的maximum likelihood的一個method
That's because your data are all frequency
那因為你的data都是frequency
So you are doing a test with the highest probability
所以你是做一個最大概是率的一個test
What about this?
那這樣子呢
I understand a little bit
我就有一點點懂
Because there is something in it including logistic test and so on
因為裡面有一點包括logistic test等等之類
As for some tests, we usually have an f test
那一些test呢我們通常就相當一個f test的
a two-tailed test
一個雙尾測驗
But I saw some results from your test
但是我又看到你test的有一些結果呢
Significant or not
有顯著有不顯著
but there are positive and negative
但是有正負
Then this is a challenge for me
那這個是對我是一個挑戰
I never thought of something like edge analysis
我從來沒有想到類似邊緣分析
F test in analysis method
分析法裡面的F test
Another conclusion can be drawn from the government
可以從政府裡面另外下一個結論
This is why I want to go back and go well
這也是我要回去好好去
to think for yourself and to learn something
去自己要思考會學習一些的東西
Another thing is
另外一個事情就是
I'm a little confused
我有點疑惑的是
Usually we do a test
通常我們做一個 test
We all assume that my sampling space is
我們都是假設我這個取樣的空間是
is stable
是穩定的
is constant
是不變的
but the one on your side
但是你這邊的那個
20 years before and after the change
變化前後有20年
Of course you have some test
當然你有一些 test
very very very correct
很很很很正確的
Because I want to compare what's 20 years ago with what's 20 years from now
因為我是要比較20年前跟20年後有的事情
but some are
但是有一些是
It seems inevitable that the
好像無可避免的是在
Assume that during the 20-year period of your study
假定在你這個研究的20年期間
Society as a whole hasn't changed much
整個社會都沒有改變太多
Or is he actually stable
或者是他事實上是維持穩定的
Or maybe he wasn't disturbed too much
或者是他沒有受到太多的干擾
but i personally think
但是我個人認為
Even especially in sociology
就算是尤其是在社會學方面
Our society has not been stable in the past 20 years
我們在過去20年這個社會不是穩定的
So many factors outside of me
所以我外界的很多因素
including gender relations including
包括兩性關係包括
some of the things we talk about have actually changed a lot in 20 years
我們探討的一些東西事實上在20年來已經改變很多了
Actually changing factors
其實改變的因素
These samples are not self-generated
不是這些樣品自我產生的
but external
而是有外界的
External impact exists
外界的衝擊存在
This is all my doubts
這是通通都是我的一些疑惑
you don't need to answer thanks
你不需要回答謝謝
This is the last question for us because the Secretariat still has some
我們這個就最後一個問題因為秘書處還有一些
something to announce
事情要跟大家宣布
thanks for this
謝謝這個
Professor Fang was the senior of my National Taiwan University choir, he was our Tanner
方教授是我當年台大合唱團的學長他是我們的Tanner
A great Tanner
一個很棒的Tanner
You're doing marine research now quite differently than the social sciences
你現在做海洋研究跟社會科學院相當大不同
But let me put it simply
不過我很簡單的來講
Just now Professor Fang specifically mentioned that we are researching on the content of the problem
剛剛方教授特別提到我們在研究的問題內容上
Is it a lot of spur-of-the-moment inspiration?
是不是很多都是臨時啟發的
I think my answer should say three out of four no
我想我的答案應該說四分之三不是
because every time we have a research framework that comes up
因為我們每一次都有一個研究架構出現
where to get the topic
要從那邊去取題目
But you saw me just now I don't look back
可是你有看到我剛剛我就不再回頭
We have some ongoing issues
我們有一些持續性題目
Also write some new topics
也寫一些新增性題目
In other words, even if it is a discipline group
換句話說即使是一個管教這一個題組
After we entered university from high school in another country, we changed it a little bit.
我們從他國中高中進入大學以後我們就稍微改一下
Then we will change it a little after he admits it
然後到他承認以後我們就稍微改一下
Because maybe your parents are not around and will keep asking you
因為可能父母不在會一直問你
Who are you hanging out with? I just hope you come home earlier or pay attention to your diet
跟誰出去玩啊只希望你要早一點回家或者你飲食要注意
We will indeed change the persistent and new questions like these
像這些我們會持續性跟新增性題目的確都是會改的
The other one is right
那另外一個他講很對
between the authors for each topic
作者間對每一個題目
his request is different
他的要求不同
So he often takes samples, he only makes samples from one country and follows them all the way to the end
所以他常常取樣他只做國一樣本一路跟到底
If it is the sum of one country and three countries
假如是國一國三加起來
some say one of the parents
有的是說父母之一
If it's dead, I don't want it
假如是過世了我就不要
because with your title
因為隨著你的題目
that denominator you made
你所做的那個分母
What you see N will be different
你所看到的N是會有不同的
Well, in recent years, we hope that everyone will use the same
那麼可是我們最近幾年是希望大家用一樣的
For example just
例如剛剛
Constructive disguises like that education
像那個教育這種建構性的變相
General Universities Top Universities Private Universities
有一般大學頂尖大學 私立大學
we can all use the same topic
我們就可以大家都用一樣的題目
Like recently, some reporters seem to visit
像最近好像有一些記者訪問
Our Professor George made this
我們喬治教授做的這個
depression
憂鬱症
Some research on the sense of rating
估級感的一些研究
You will find that everyone uses some of the same topics
你就會發現大家都用一些比較一樣的題目
what about the end
那最後呢
In terms of statistics, we have a publication outside
統計方面的話我們外面有一份我們的出版品
Actually, I was just joking with Deputy Huang
其實我剛還在跟黃副開玩笑說
in our group
我們這個組裡面
probably except me
大概除了我以外
Each teaches social statistics
每一個都教社會統計
So they all know how to use
所以他們都知道用什麼樣的方法
are very complicated
都非常複雜
Then I often have to work very hard to follow
那我常常就要很努力的跟
I want to say why this topic uses this method
想說為什麼這個題目用這個方法
Use this method for that topic
那個題目用這個方法
what's the point
又是什麼道理
things like cohabitation
像同居的事情
Teacher Yang Wenshan came to my office twice to tell me
楊文山老師就到我的辦公室兩次講給我聽
I have to listen for a long time to understand
我就一定要聽很久才聽得懂
Because they all have their own algorithm
因為這些他們都有一套他們的算法
But he's right, isn't the statistic?
不過他講的對的確統計是不是
we may be with biological
我們可能跟生物
I heard the creature's leather card is very powerful
我聽說生物的皮牌很厲害
He ordered everyone to do the same thing
他跟一聲令下大家都做一樣的事
we have never heard of this
這個我們絕對沒有聽過
the other one is
那另外一個就是
20 years of change in this social context
在這個社會脈絡方面這20年來的改變
often to inspire us to add some questions
常常以啟發我們新增一些問題
For example, when someone asked about the economic bubble in 2008 and 2009
例如在那個剛剛有一個誰問2008 2009經濟泡沫的時候
we specifically asked
我們就特別問到
family financial instability
家庭經濟不穩定性
We have a set of questions that ask you if the following things happened to you last year
我們有一套的題目就是問你去年有沒有發生以下的事情
Does anyone remember will ask
有沒有人記得就會問
These include the father's cause, the mother's cause, or one of the parents
其中包括父親事業母親事業或者父母之一
death or divorce etc.
死亡或離婚等等
I hope to be able to capture this
就希望能夠capture這種
special circumstances
特殊的一些情況
but of course
不過當然
Because after this whole topic goes down,
因為這個整個的題目下去之後
you can't move around
你是不可以隨便亂動的
Even now we sometimes say how to write like this at that time
甚至我們現在有時候我們就說那時候怎麼這樣寫
Can't write Chinese well enough
中文寫的不夠好
you can't change
你也不能改
because you already use people like this
因為你已經這樣用人
have to keep using it continuously
就得一直連續地用下去
So I thank Professor Fang
所以我謝謝方教授
Remind us something we really still
提醒我們一些我們真的還
I hope that in the future, when others do research,
希望將來大家別人做研究的時候
there may be a place to work hard
可以有在努力的地方
Thanks
謝謝
ok ask again
好 再問一下
secretary group
秘書組
what are you announcing
你們來宣布哪些事情
thank you before we do this
那我們這個之前先謝謝
Professor Ying's wonderful speech
影教授精采的演講
applause
掌聲
Secretariat report
秘書處報告
Today's speech is by Mr. Yi Xinchun before his retirement
今日演講是依信春老師退休前
The last big Chinese speech
最後一場的大型中文演講
Colleague Xu Weisuo in order to thank the teacher
徐維索同事為了感謝老師
dedication over the years
多年來的奉獻
Make special use of tonight's occasion
特別利用今晚的場合
Thanks Teacher Yi
感謝依老師
We also wish Mr. Yi's retirement life
我們也祝福依老師的退休生活
Still rich and brilliant
依舊豐富精采
Thanks
謝謝
Then you can get a small gift
然後即可獲敬美小禮
Thank you for your participation today
謝謝您今天的參與